Vol. 44 No. 2 IPSJ Journal Feb. 2003Regular PaperIntegrated Network Operation Baselining and Adaptive Detection of Faults and Performance ProblemsHassan Hajji† and Behrouz H. Far††Detection of network problems is a crucial step in automating network management. It has a direct impact on the accuracy of fault, performance and security management functions. In this paper, we propose an adaptive technique for network fault and performance detection. Network operations normal baseline is parameterized as a finite mixture model, and model parameters are estimated from data using the Expectation Maximization algorithm. We propose a novel method for online residual generation, based on repeated identification of model parameters. The resulting multivariate residuals are shown to be approximately Normal with the mean 0 and unit variance under normal conditions, and the mean jumps suddenly to a different value, once anomaly occurs. To achieve fast detection, we formulate the problem of detection as a sequential disruption problem, where the task is to detect departures from the baseline distribution as soon as the disruption happens. An analytical expression of false alarm rate allows us to choose the threshold, automatically. Experimental results on a real network showed that the monitoring agent is able to detect even slight changes in the characteristics of the network, while maintaining a low false alarm rate.1. IntroductionNetworks and distributed processing systems have become an important substrate of mod- ern information technology. The rapid growth of these systems throughout the workplace has given rise to a discontinuity in expertise of hu- man operators to manage them. There is a need for automating the management functions to re- duce network operations and management cost.Detection of network problems is a crucial step in automating network management. It has a direct impact on the accuracy of fault, performance and security management func- tions. From a control viewpoint, well designed fault and performance problems detection algo- rithms enhance the network control capability, by providing timely indication of network incip- ient problems. The possibility of early detec- tion of performance degradation can alleviate the constant fire-fighting of network managers. Early warnings from the monitoring agent can trigger preventive actions, and serious and ex- pensive outages can be avoided.Most of the existing research assumed that the alarm generating mechanism is accu- rate, and network problems are given a pri- ori 6),7),25) . Current practice in network man- agement rely on user-defined thresholds for de-† IBM Research, Tokyo Research Laboratory, Japan †† Department of Electrical and Computer Engineer-ing, University of Calgary, Canadatection. Alarms are generated when some vari- able of interest crosses a predefined threshold. Generally, the predefined value of the thresh- old is no more than an estimation of the nor- mal range within which the measured feature is believed to operate. Not only there is lit- tle objective insights on how to choose these thresholds, but also there is a risk of missing subtle changes in the network state 5) . In addi- tion, the complexity and size of current network systems makes them vulnerable to novel faults and performance degradation patterns.The main difficulty of network anomaly de- tection is the lack of a general definition of what constitutes normal behavior 8). The dy- namics of the network normal operations need to be identified from routine operation data. To this end,11) characterizes the normal behavior by different templates, obtained by taking the standard deviations of observations (typically Ethernet load and packets count), at different operating times. An observation is declared ab- normal if it exceeds the upper bound of the en- velope. Given the bursty nature of network traffic, the standard deviation estimates are likely to be distorted, making subtle changes in the network state go undetected. To miti- gate the effect of the non-stationary nature of network traffic 5), considered the model formedThis research is done while authors at Department of Information and Computer Science, Saitama Uni- veristy, Japan  386
Vol. 44 No. 2 Network Operation Baselining and Adaptive Detection of Faults 387by segmenting time series obtained form SNMP MIB objects. Observations are declared abnor- mal if they do not fit an auto-regressive model of the traffic inside segments. In20) the obser- vation are declared abnormal after a statistical test with the mean of 24-hour period sample. In these approaches, the assumption of piece-wise constancy of the traffic is questionable, since the traffic burst is not sustained long enough to allow accurate estimation, and the combin- ing scheme for correlating different alarms from the objects is ad-hoc.In this paper, we address the problem of per- formance problems detection in IP-Networks, where the knowledge about the problems to be detected is not required. The emphasis is on fast detection with minimal human super- vision – an important requirement for reducing potential impact of problems on network ser- vices users. We propose a model of the net- work operations in terms of MIB objects de- pendencies, and we show that the parametric characterization of this dependency can be de- scribed as a finite mixture of simple regression models. Model parameters are identified from routine operation data, using the expectation maximization algorithm.A new method for residual generation, based on successive parameter identification, is intro- duced. The residuals are shown to be approx- imately multivariate Normal, with mean zero under normal operations, and sudden jumps in this mean are characteristics of abnormal con- ditions. The detection problem is formulated as a change point problem. A real-time on- line change detection algorithm is designed to processes, sequentially, the residuals and raise an alarm as soon as the anomaly occurs. We motivate this formulation through a real prob- lem scenario that occurred in Saitama univer- sity network. The proposed approach requires neither the set of faults and performance degra- dation nor the thresholds to be supplied by the user. Experimental results showed the effec- tiveness of the method on real data. A very low alarm rate and a high detection capability has been demonstrated.This paper is arranged as follows: Section 2 introduces our proposed model of the network normal behavior, and the learning algorithm for parameter identification from routine oper- ation data. Section 3 introduces our proposed approach for residual generation, and the for- mulation of the network problem detection. InTable 1 Object clusters for performance problem detection.  Dependent Vari- able (Y) ifInNUcastPkts ipInReceives ipInDeliversipForwDatagrams ifOutPkts for all interfaces ifOutNUcastPktsIndependent Variable (X)ifInPkts for all interfaces ipInReceives + ifInPkts (loop- back interface)ipInReceives - ipInDelivers ipForwDatagrams + ipOutRe- quests             Section 4, we present results of our experiments in a real network. We conclude in section 6.2. Normal Operations BaseliningMIB objects are designed to reflect the activ- ity of the network at each protocol layer entity. The goal of this section is to characterize net- work normal behavior using these objects, and to identify network model parameters from rou- tine operation data.2.1 Network ModelOur proposed model is to define the network normal behavior model in terms of the rela- tionships between selected MIB objects. That is, instead of studying individual objects, the normal behavior of the network is defined as the parametric characterization of clusters of dependent variables in the interface and net- work layers. The node’s view of the of the network behavior is, then, the aggregation of these models. Table 1 shows object dependen- cies at the network and interface level, as can be extracted from the functional requirement of TCP/IP protocol stack, or case diagrams 19).This approach has three main benefits. First, examining the relationship between dependent variables provides a robust method for detect- ing network anomalies: it allows the model to interpret individual variable values in conjunc- tion with dependent variable values. For ex- ample, the number of interface errors alone is not a clear-cut indication of network problems unless studied in relation to the total amount of inbound traffic 9). Second, the statistical characteristics of individual variables is non- stationary, and better characterization of nor- mal behavior can be obtained by examining explicitly variables dependency. Segmentation of individual variables, as proposed in Refs. 5), 20), overlooks the effect of variables on each other. Clearly, the segmentation of the vari- able ipInReceives, for instance, could be better
388 IPSJ Journal Feb. 2003done if all incoming packets ifInPkts are taken into account. Third, the specific nature of the MIB-II12) shows that structural change in the dependency between these variables is a symp- tom of an abnormal behavior. For example, if the relation between ifInPkts and ipInReceives changes, it is because of errors caused by lack of buffer space, line noise or unknown proto- cols packets and so on. In this sense, selected objects form a sufficient subset that needs to be continuously monitored. In addition, it is guaranteed that these variables statistics are available across most operating systems kernels. Currently, there is little support for detailed in- terface error statistics.Most of operating systems share the same de- pendency as in Table 1, except for some systems that put loop-back packets directly in the IP in- put queue, rather than requiring network inter- face cards to read their own transmissions. We can account for this case by adding the loop- back packets to the ipInReceives as shown in Table 1.2.2 Objects Dependency Parametric ModelTo be able to identify the network operation parameters from operation data, we have to de- fine a parametric model for network operations. Our approach to network model parameteriza- tion is to view each cluster (X, Y ) as switching between different regimes, where each regime is a simple linear regression model. This is a form of what referred to in the literature as switching regression 13),15). The observations (xi, yi) are generated by one of the K linear regression, as shown in the following equations:yi =b′kxi+εki k=1,...,K (1)tions. Each regime k has a mixing probability, denoted by πk .Finite mixture models for network opera- tion baselining captures both clusters that may be described parsimoniously by linear relation- ships, and more generally non-linear dynamics of any given cluster. In fact, finite Gaussian mixture models are general enough to approxi- mate any continuous function with a finite num- ber of discontinuities, under appropriate regu- larity conditions 22) . For any cluster of variables (X, Y ) that are linearly related, or even locally linear with slowly time-varying parameters, an adaptive algorithm with suitably chosen forget- ting factor can track the model parameters. In general, however, breaks in the linear relation- ship are normal, and the idea then is to explic- itly accommodate these breaks in the network model. The resulting model is, then, a mixture of regimes, where each regime describe a given mode of network operations.The network normal behavior is then charac- terized by the parameters of the finite mixture model. In the next subsection, we show how these parameters are identified.2.3 Learning Model ParametersIdentifying the network normal operations from routine operation data amounts to es- timate the parameter θ of the switching re- gression. The vector θ consists of the vec- tors b1,...,bK, the variances σ1,...,σK and the mixing probabilities π1 , . . . , πK . Given a training set of N independent and identically distributed data points (xi, yi), the Maximum Likelihood (ML) estimator is the vector θˆ that maximizes the likelihood function L(θ), given by: K ′2 p(yi|xi) = √πk exp−(yi −bkxi)θˆ = arg max L(θ) θ(5) (6)2  (7)  i=1 2πσk 2σk2(2) N  K i=1 k=1πkfik For the case of single variables in Table 1, such as IfInNUcastPkts, we have:−(yi −bkxi) 2σk2L(θ) =fik = √ 1 exp ′   yi = mk + εki k = 1, . . . , Kp(yi) =(3) (4)2πσkFor the case of mixture of Normal distributions, K π k − ( y i − m k ) 2 √2πσ exp 2σ2fik is given by:1 2πσk −(yi −mk)2 2    i=1 k kThe errors εk are assumed to be Gaussian, with mean 0 and variance σk. The column vector bk is made of the slope and the intercept for the regime k. Abusing the notation slightly, the in- teger K denotes the number of regimes, for both the mixture of regression and Normal distribu-fik = √exp2σk(8)   If we note (x,y,z) the complete sample infor- mation, and given the values of the separation variable z, that assigns each observation to its corresponding regime, maximum likelihood es-
Vol. 44 No. 2 Network Operation Baselining and Adaptive Detection of Faults 389timation is straightforward. In the absence of this complete information explicit maximiza- tion of the likelihood function is not tractable. However, viewing the separation variable z as missing, the estimation can be formally identi- fied with the Expectation Maximization (EM) algorithm 4) . The EM algorithm 2),16) estimate the unknown parameter θ by iteratively max- imizing the expected log likelihood Q(θ|θ′). Given an initial parameter θ0, the following two steps are iterated until convergence:E-Step: Given a current approximation θm, determine the expected log likelihood Q(θ|θm):w x (y −bn−1x ) n n−1 knnn k nbk=bk +  n wkix2 (12) i=1 i b0k = ˆbk(13)For the case of mixture of Normal distributions, the mean mk of each regime k is updated as follows:wkn(yn − mn−1) mnk=mnk+  n k (14)  N  K i=1 k=1w = πkfik ki  K πfWhere bnk and mnk are the estimate of the slope parameter bk and mean mk at iteration n, re- spectively. Xn is a n × 1 vector made of the re- gressor xi, and Xn′ is its transpose vector. Wkn is the n×n diagonal matrix, made of the weights wki. The initial parameters b0 and μ0 are the estimates obtained using the batch EM (Sec. 2.3). It is worth nothing to note that Eq. (12) is very similar to the recursive parameter es- timation proposed in21), where parameters are updated online for each new observation. In the sequel, we are interested only in the changes of the parameters bk, and mk of the network model.Under normal conditions, the difference be- tween the successive values bn and bn−1 is ex- pected to fluctuate around zero. This difference should not drift constantly in a fixed direction. On the other hand, if this difference drifts sys- tematically over long duration, then the new observations are generated by a different model, and the recursion in Eq. (12) will alter the pa- rameter b to its new value. The idea, then, is to generate the residuals based on the K-variate random variable (bn −bn−1). The mean value of this difference is a good indicator of the health of the network.There is two major advantages of the residu- als generated this way. First, successive identi- fication of the parameters allows the model to adaptively track local changes in its parame- ters. It is unrealistic to assume that the model parameters will remain exactly the same over all the operating times of the network. Sec- ond, the difference (bn −bn−1) does not depend on the “true” value of the parameter b. This is very important since, in practice, we do not know this “true” value, and the only available information is the value ˆb, estimated from the data. Approximating b with ˆb, and studying the difference (bn − ˆb) is possible, but our experi- ments showed that this approach is inefficient.Q(θ|θm) =wki log(fik)(9) (10)m0k =mˆk(15)i=1 wki k=1 k ikM-Step: The new refined estimate θm+1 isthe solution of the maximization:θm+1 = arg max Q(θ|θm) (11)θ∈ΘThe EM algorithm has a number of appealing properties. It is numerically stable, in the sense that the incomplete data likelihood is increased at each iteration 2) . Also, since the M-Step re- lies on the complete data, the maximization in this step is analytically solvable. In fact, in our case the M-Step is simply the weighted least squares, where the weights are wki, obtained by calculating the posterior probability of each observation with respect to each of the regimes, as shown in Eq. (10). Similar reasoning can be done for the case of finite Normal distributions mixtures.3. Online Network Problems Detec- tionThe previous section showed how the dynam- ics of the networks are identified. In this sec- tion we turn to discuss how the residuals are generated, and our formulation of the problem of anomaly detection.3.1 Residual GenerationThe residual generation method we propose is based on the algorithm for parameter esti- mation. After convergence of the learning algo- rithm (Sec. 2.3), we keep updating the slopes bk and the means mk of each regime, assuming that only one iteration of the EM algorithm is used for each new observation (xn , yn ). It can be shown, that:
390IPSJ Journal Feb. 2003  Fig. 1Behavior of the drifts of two typical clusters of objects, (a) drifts (bnk − bn−1) and (bn−ˆbk) under the same network conditions, for the cluster(a)(b)kk nn−1n(IfInPkts, ipInReceives), (b) drifts (mk −mk ) and (mk −mˆ k) underthe same network conditions, for the variable ifOutNUcastPkts.  (a) (b)Fig. 2 Residuals plots under the same network conditions as in Fig. 1: (a) Univariate residuals ekn for regime k of the switching regression, as given by Eq.(16), (b) ekn for finite Normal mixtures, as given by Eq. (18).Figure 1 compares both differences for a dura-tion of one hour under the same network condi-tions. Results are shown only for one of the tworegimes of the cluster, denoted by k. It is clearthat the difference (bnk − ˆbk) is not symmetricaround zero, while the difference (bn − bn−1) is kkboth symmetric and very close to zero under normal conditions. We showed empirically 3) that the K-variate residuals en given by:en = (mn − mn−1)T Λ−1(mn − mn−1)(18) Λ=diag   kn k (19) √w σˆ   ni=1 wkiare approximately Normal, with mean zero un- en = (bn − bn−1)T Λ−1(bn − bn−1)  √ Λ = diag wknxnσˆk XnT WknXn(16)(17)der network normal conditions. Note that en given in Eq. (16) (respectively Eq. (18)) is simply the difference (bn − bn−1) (respectively (mn − mn−1) ), scaled such that its variance- covariance matrix becomes Identity. Figure 2 shows the behavior of the residuals ekn under the same network conditions as in Fig. 1. It can be seen that these residuals are stable, and their mean is very close to 0.In summary, network operations are charac- terized by the distribution of the residuals en.  For the case of mixture of Normal distributions, the residuals en are given by:
Vol. 44No. 2Network Operation Baselining and Adaptive Detection of Faults 391  (a) (b)Fig.3 Residuals generated by one of the two regimes of (ifInPkts, IpIn- Receives), under abnormal conditions: (a) structural break variables relationship, (b) slight change in the mean of the residuals just before the break.We showed that, under normal operations, the residuals en are approximately Normal with mean zero and variance Identity matrix. The next section shows the behavior of the resid- uals under abnormal conditions, and how we formulate and solve the detection problem.3.2 Anomaly DetectionAnomaly detection is determining the dis- crepancy between the normal behavior and the predicted behavior. Figure 3 shows the be- havior of the residuals generated by the model under a real abnormal condition that affected Saitama university network, due to badly for- matted packets. As shown in Fig. 3-a, this ab- normal condition causes a sudden jump in the mean of the residuals. Fig. 3-b shows the behav- ior of the residuals just before the sudden jump in the mean. Interestingly, we notice that the sudden jump is preceded by a slight change in the mean of residuals. If the detection approach is designed to be sensitive to slight changes in the operating characteristics of the network, we could have predicted the problem of Fig.3 at least 19 minutes before it became serious. The problem could have been avoided, or at least addressed immediately after its occurrence. In general, however, we do not expect all prob- lems to present signs to allow their prediction. In this case, we require our detection method to raise alarm as soon as change in the mean occurs.Consider the residuals Ecn obtained by ob- serving sequentially the residuals ei from time point c to n. Under the normal operations of the network, the sample of en follows a K-variate Normal distribution with mean 0 and Identity covariance matrix (Sec. 3.1). At some unknown time point c, a change happens in the model, and the new generated residuals shift to a new distribution. The goal is to find a decision function and a stopping rule that de- tects this change and raise an alarm as soon as possible, under a controlled false alarm rate. This formulation is known in sequential anal- ysis literature as the disruption problem. The main difference with classical hypothesis testing is that the sample size is a function of the obser- vations made so far (i.e., not fixed a priori), and the distribution of the residuals is known, when the process being monitored, is in control. The goal is to achieve fast detection of change, by using no more than the necessary sample size to decide whether an alarm is to be raised or not.It is well-known that for known probability distribution after change, Page-Lorden cumu- lative sum (CUSUM)10),14) test is optimal, in the sense that it minimizes the delay to detec- tion, among all tests with a given false alarm rate. However, in the present case of network anomaly detection, we do not have a priori knowledge about the distribution probability after change Pθ1 , and the change point c. The common extension of Page-Lorden CUSUM test consists of estimating the post-change dis- tribution mean, and the change point from the data. This approach is known as the General- ized Likelihood Ratio (GLR) test 1),23). That is, the unknown parameter θ1 of the distribution of Pθ1 (ei) after change, and the change point c are
392 IPSJ Journal Feb. 2003estimated from data, using the maximum likeli- hood estimator. The resulting decision function is given by:4. Evaluation and ResultsThe network monitoring algorithms de- scribed earlier has been implemented in a real networks. This section discusses how the data is collected, and the results that validate the agent capabilities.4.1 Experimental SettingThe network traffic is monitored using the standard MIB-II information base. To ensure reliable data sets, the agent is implemented to fetch the network statistics directly from the OS kernel. The agent is written in C++, and currently runs on both Solaris 2.6 and AIX 4.1. To validate the agent results, we implemented a program to access the underlying data-link layer for fault injection. The program is written using the Data Link Provider Interface (DLPI), on Solaris 2.6 operating system. The goal is not to simulate all possible faults, but rather to prove that alarms generated by the agent are, effectively, due to abnormal network conditions.4.2 Implementation AspectsTo allow our model to track time varyingparameters, we introduce an exponential for-getting factor 0 < ζ ≤ 1, that reduces theeffect of old observations, much in the sameRn = sup supln P(Ecn|θ1,c) 1≤c≤n θ1 P (Ecn|θ0)Tn =inf{n:Rn >λ}(20)(21) In our case, where pre-change and post- change distributions are Normal, the maximiza- tion problem of Eq. (20) can be worked out ex- plicitly. It has a simple form, given by:S0 =(0,...,0)Tn = inf{n : max0≤c<n(22)(23)T  n Sn =∥ Sn − Sc ∥ √i=1ei> λ}  The equation assumes that after change, the distribution of the residuals is still Normal, but with different mean. For the abnormal case, it is hard to obtain an unbiased fit of the post- change distribution Pθ1 (ei). Fortunately such accurate estimation is not crucial. What is needed is that, when an anomaly occurs, the closest Normal distribution, obtained by maxi- mum likelihood estimation, has a mean signifi- cantly different from zero.3.3 Tuning the Threshold λSo far we have introduced the decision func- tion and the stopping rule used for online detec- tion of network faults and performance degra- dation. The remainder of our problem set-up concerns the choice of the design threshold λ.It can be shown that the expectation of the stopping rule, under no change denoted by E∞(T), is given by17):way as proposed in24). Evaluating the sumΓ(K/2)2K/2exp(λ2/2) E∞(T ) ∼ K   λ 2λ 0 xv (x)dxasλ → ∞ (24)Unfortunately, Eq. (23) can not be written re- cursively. Consequently, the number of resid- uals to be inspected can grow large. To cir- cumvent this difficulty, we use a moving hori- zon of fixed length, where the starting point of the horizon moves one step forward as new ob- servation are made available to inspection. For the mean false alarm rate (Sec. 3.3), it is fixed to 8640, which corresponds to 24-hours period, given that samples are collected every 10 sec- onds. Finally, for the number of components K, it was found empirically that at most 4 regimes are enough to describe the data satisfactorily. Work is underway to infer the number of com- ponents automatically from data.4.3 Detection CapabilityThe agent detection capability is first illus- trated using the network problem, introduced earlier in Section 3.2. The problem occurred in Saitama university, on November 24th, 2000. It showed up as a streaming network interface card card sending excessively badly formattedn − c n w x2 (Eq. (12), Sec. 3.1) is then replaced i = 1 n k i iby i=1 ζiwkix2i . Similar modification is done for finite Normal mixture parameter updating (Eq. (14)). v(x) = 2x2exp   ∞ −21n−1Φ −xn1/2   2, x>0 (25) where Φ denotes the normal distribution func- tion. For calculation, see17),18) for an approxi- mation of v(x). Not surprisingly, Eq. (24) turns out to be the mean time between false alarms. It follows that, given a desired false alarm rate, we can recover the design threshold λ, by solv- ing Eq. (24).
Vol. 44No. 2Network Operation Baselining and Adaptive Detection of Faults 393  Fig. 4Behavior of the test static for the problem that occurred in Saitama university network.(a) (b)  (a) (b)  Fig. 5(c) (d)Behavior of the test statistic corresponding to excessive ARP packets, excessive inbound broadcasts, excessive outbound broadcasts, and IP packet loss problems: (a) IP packet discards, (b) Outbound broadcast packets, (c) Inbound broadcast packets, (d) Inbound ARP packets.packets. Figure 4 shows the behavior of the residuals and test statistic as detected by the cluster (ifInPkts, ipInReceives). As shown in the figure, it takes approximately 30 samples(5 minutes) to detect the slight change in the residuals. In this particular case, the threshold is crossed 19 minutes before the sudden disrup- tion. It could have been possible to address the
394 IPSJ Journal Feb. 2003problem, proactively, before it became serious, or at least draw the attention of network oper- ators earlier, before the impact of the problem is felt by all network users.Detection capability of the agent is tested with other problems. The obtained results are shown in Fig. 5. For IP packet loss and exces- sive outbound broadcasts, appropriately assem- bled packets are sent every two seconds. For the remaining problems, assembled packets are in- jected every one second. It can be seen that the agent could detect all of these problems, with reasonably short delay.We note that, apart from reasons given in Section 2.1 for defining network model as the parametric characterization of dependent ob- jects, there is no MIB counter for ARP oper- ations. Also, for the problem of packet loss induced by assembling Ethernet packets with non-existent protocol type, some kernels do not have any entry for this type of errors, even if this object is part of the standard MIB-II in- formation base. For IP operations, one can easily check that IpInDelivers and IpInReceives can be sometimes very large, without noticing any change in IP related errors. This is true even when we take into consideration the fact that loopback packets are to be added to Ip- InReceives. With current under-instrumented networks, our approach to network modeling and performance problems detection can pro- vide useful insights about incipient problems.In conclusion, we showed that our proposed approach is very efficient. In all the results re- ported here, we actually stress tested the agent detection capability. The total amount of all in- jected packets is smoothed over the whole test duration. In practice, network problems are ex- pected to induce large magnitude changes in the model residuals. The detection is expected to even work better.4.4 Alarm RateIdeally, we would like to estimate the false alarm rate, given that the network is operating normally. Unfortunately, it is difficult to gain perfect knowledge about all the subtle changes in the network behavior. Instead, Table 2 shows the average alarm rate per hour, for data collected during a period of 24-hours.We note that ifOutNUcastPkts is very stable, recording a zero alarm rate per 24-hours. The same comment is also true for ifInNUcastPkts. This raises questions about whether the switch- ing regression model adds any accuracy to theTable 2 Average number of alarms per hour for each of the clusters of network model.   ClustersAverage alarmrate per hour ifInNUcastPkts   0.04 ipInReceives,   0.50 ifInPktsipInReceives,   0.08 ipInDeliversipForwDatagrams,   0.04 ☆ ipInReceive - ipInDelivers       ifOutPkts, ipForwDatagrams+ ipOutRequestsifOutNUcastPkts   0.000.16    Fig. 6CPU time percentage consumed by the monitoring process.model. It is probably enough to model all the variable by a finite mixture model. We plan to investigate this question in detail in the future.5. CPU TimeThe final aspect we investigate in our pro- posed approach is the amount of CPU time consumed by the monitoring agent. In this ex- periment, another process is set to sample the agent’s CPU time usage, every 10 seconds. The agent runs on SunOS Release 5.8, with SPARC CPU (333MHz). Figure 6 shows the CPU time consumed by the agent, for monitoring si- multaneously 10 variables, 20 variables, and 30 variables.It can be clearly seen that the monitoring consumes a very small amount of the CPU time. The obtained results shows that for monitoring 10 variables simultaneously, the process con- sumes an average of 0.34 CPU time. The av- erage is calculated by sampling the CPU usage every 10 seconds, for an overall duration of 24☆ Results are from an internal router of Saitama Uni- versity network. 
Vol. 44 No. 2 Network Operation Baselining and Adaptive Detection of Faults 395hours. Scaling this figure to 20 variables, an av- erage of 0.76 CPU usage has been recorded. Fi- nally with 30 variables 1.27 have been achieved. It is safe, then, to claim that our approach can scale well with large number of variables.Overall results shows a highly efficient net- work monitoring scheme. The methods for both monitoring are generic to be readily tailored to specific scenarios. It is, however, important to note that convergence of learning algorithm for parameter identification needs very large data sets. It is recommended that a sample of at least two week to one month of data points is to be used for normal operations baselining.6. ConclusionIn this paper, we developed an online tech- nique for fast detection of performance prob- lems in IP-Networks. We proposed a model of the network operations in terms of MIB objects dependencies, and we showed that the para- metric characterization of this dependency is amenable to a finite mixture model. Model pa- rameters are identified from routine operation data, using the expectation maximization algo- rithm. A new method for residual generation, based on successive parameter identification, is introduced. The residuals are shown to be ap- proximately Normal, with mean zero under nor- mal operations, and sudden jumps in this mean are characteristics of abnormal conditions. A real-time online change detection algorithm is designed to process the residuals sequentially, and raise an alarm as soon as the anomaly oc- curs. The proposed approach requires neither the set of faults and performance degradation nor the thresholds to be supplied by the user. Experimental results showed the effectiveness of the method on real data. A low false alarm rate and a high detection capability has been demonstrated.References1) Basseville, M. and Nikiforov, I.V.: Detection of Abrupt Changes: Theory and Application, Prentice-Hall (1993).2) Dempster, A., Laird, N. and Rubin, D.: Maxi- mum Likelihood from Incomplete Data via the EM Algorithm, J.R. Statist. Soc. B, Vol.39, pp.1–38 (1977).3) Hajji, H. and Far, B.H.: Continuous Network Monitoring for Fast Detection of Performance Problems, Proc. 2001 International Symposium on Performance Evaluation of Computer andTelecommunication Systems (2001).4) Hartley, M.J.: Comment on “Estimating mix- tures of Normal Distributions and Switch- ing Regressions”, J. Am. Stat. Assoc., Vol.73,pp.738–741 (1978).5) Hood, C. and Ji, C.: Proactive Network FaultDetection, IEEE Trans. Reliability, Vol.46,No.3, pp.333–341 (1997).6) Jakobson, G. and Weissman, M.D.: AlarmCorrelation, IEEE Network, pp.52–59 (1993). 7) Katzela, I. and Schwarz, M.: Schemes For Fault Identification is Communication Net- works, IEEE/ACM Trans. Networking, Vol.3,pp.753–764 (1995).8) LaBarre, L.: Management by Exception: OSIevent generation, reporting, and logging, Proc. Second International Symposium on Integrated Network Management (1991).9) Leinwand, A. and Conroy, K.F.: Network management, a practical perspective, 2nd Edi- tion, Addison-Wesley (1996).10) Lorden, G.: Procedures for reacting to a change in distribution, Annals of Mathemati- cal Statistics, Vol.42, pp.1897–1908 (1971).11) Maxion, R.A. and Feather, F.E.: A Case Study of Ethernet Anomalies in a Distributed Computing Environments, IEEE Transactions on Reliability, Vol.39, No.4, pp.433–443 (1990).12) McCloghrie, K. and Rose, M.: Management Information Base for Network Management of TCP/IP-based internets: MIB-II, RFC 1213 (1991).13) McLachlan, G.J. and Basford, K.E.: Mixture Models: Inference and Application to Cluster- ing, New York, Dekker (1988).14) Page, E.S.: Continuous Inspection Schemes, Biometrika, Vol.41, pp.100–115 (1954).15) Quandt, R.E.: A New Approach to Estimat- ing Switching Regressions, J. Am. Stat. Assoc., Vol.67, No.338, pp.306–310 (1972).16) Redner, R.A. and Walker, H.F.: Mixture Den- sities, Maximum Likelihood and the EM Algo- rithm, SIAM Review, Vol.26, No.2, pp.195–239 (1984).17) Seigmund, D. and Venkatraman, E.S.: Using the Generalized Likelihood Ratio Statistic for Sequential Detection of a Change Points, The Annals of Statistics, Vol.23, No.1, pp.255–271 (1995).18) Siegmund, D.: Sequential Analysis: Tests and Confidence Intervals, Springer, New York (1985).19) Stalling, W.: The SNMPv1, SNMPv2 and RMON, Addison-Wesley, Reading, MA, USA (1999).20) Thottan, M. and Ji, C.: Statistical Detection of Enterprise Network problems, Journal of
396 IPSJ JournalFeb. 2003Network and Systems Management (1999). 21) Titterington, D.M.: Recursive Parameter Es- timation using Incomplete, Journal of Royal Statistics Society, Serie B, Vol.46, No.2,pp.257–267 (1984).22) Vlassis, N.A.: A Kurtosis-Based Dynamic Ap-proach to Gaussian Mixture Modeling, IEEE Transactions On Systems, Man, And Cybernet- ics, Part A, Vol.29, No.4, pp.393–399 (1999).23) Willsky, A.S. and Jones, H.L.: A General- ized Likelihood Ratio Approach to the Detec- tion and Estimation of Jumps in Linear Sys- tems, IEEE Transactions on Automatic Con- trol, Short Paper, pp.108–112 (1976).24) Weinstein, E., Feder, M. and Oppenheim, A.V.: Sequential algorithms for parameter esti- mation based on Kullback-Leibler information measure, IEEE Trans. Acous., Speech, Signal Processing, Vol.38, No.9, pp.1652–1654 (1990).25) Yemini, S., Kliger, S., Mozes, E., Yemini, Y. and Ohsie, D.: High speed and robust event correlation, IEEE Communication Magazine, pp.82–90 (1996).(Received August 7, 2001) (Accepted November 5, 2002)Hassan Hajji received his BS.c degree from Mohamed Pre- mier University, Morocco in 1995, MSc. and Ph.D degrees from Saitama University, Japan in 1999 and 2002, respectively. He is currently with IBM re-search, Tokyo Research Laboratory, Japan. His current research interests include network and system management, traffic modeling and anal- ysis, and autonomic computing. Dr. Hassan Hajji is a member of IEEE computer society and IPSJ.Behrouz Homayoun Farreceived BSc. and MSc. degrees in Electrical Engineering in 1993 and 1986, respectively, from Tehran University, Iran. He has received his Ph.D degree from Chiba University, Japan in 1990.He is currently an Associate Professor at the Department of Electrical and Computer Engi- neering, University of Calgary, Canada, where he is the coordinator of the Intelligent Systems Group at the University of Calgary. The re- search fields of his interests are automatic pro- gramming, software quality management and distributed AI. Dr. Far is a member of the ACM, IEEE computer society, JSAI, and IPSJ.   