Vol. 44 No. 5 IPSJ Journal May 2003Regular PaperJPEG Encoder Design Space ExplorationUsing the ASIP Development System: PEAS-IIIShinsuke Kobayashi,† Kentaro Mita,† Yoshinori Takeuchi†† and Masaharu Imai††In this paper, JPEG encoder application, one of DSP applications, was designed using the ASIP development system: PEAS-III. Instructions for JPEG encoder, such as DCT instruc- tion, and butterfly instructions, were added to the initial design. Area, performance, and power consumption of processors were estimated using generated HDL description, compiler, and assembler. From experimental results, 12 architectures can be designed in 16 hours, and designer can select an optimal architecture that matches design constraints considering hardware cost, clock frequency and execution cycles.1. IntroductionThere are two approaches to realize applica- tion domain specific embedded systems. One is to use general purpose processors and ASICs (Application Specific Integrated Circuits), and the other is to use ASIPs (Application Specific Instruction set Processors). One of the advan- tages of the second approach is that better im- plementations can be realized by introducing cost-effective instructions suitable for specific applications. In the ASIP design, it is also im- portant to search for a processor architecture that matches the target application. To achieve this goal, it is essential to estimate design qual- ity of architecture candidates that have dif- ferent instruction sets, pipeline stage counts, and combinations of hardware resources. Here, design quality means area, performance, and power consumption of a design. Because there are many architectural parameters, there exist a huge number of processor architecture candi- dates, which makes it difficult to find an opti- mal architecture in a short design time. In this case, the ASIP development system plays an important role to estimate design quality and develop target processors.Conventional approaches to ASIP develop- ment can be classified into two kinds. One approach is a “parameterized generic proces- sor core” such as PEAS-I 1) , Satsuki 2) , Meta- Core 3) , CASTLE 4) , Xtensa 5) and so on. Their processor models usually have basic instruction† Graduate School of Engineering and Science, Osaka University†† Graduate School of Information Science and Tech- nology, Osaka Universitysets and a synthesizable ASIP description is generated by adding predefined or user defined instructions to the basic instruction set. Ar- chitectures of these processors ease to develop the parameterized retargettable compiler, but in many cases have little flexibility on pipeline structure and instruction variations. Hence, the variety of architecture candidates by these sys- tems is limited with respect to pipeline stage count, instruction format and micro-operation for each pipeline.Another approach is based on “proces- sor specification languages” such as nML 6), ISDL 7) , LISA 8) , FlexWare 9) , EXPRES- SION 10), AIDL 11), and Hamabe, et al. 12)’s ap- proach. The processor specification languages nML, ISDL, LISA, FlexWare and EXPRES- SION are originally developed to design a com- piler, simulator and other tools for software de- velopment. The instruction behavior and the structure of the target processor are described in these specification languages. The compiler and other tools can be generated using these languages, but it is difficult to generate syn- thesizable HDL descriptions from these lan- guages. Because it is not enough resource spec- ification including timing specification, control signal information and so on to generate HDL descriptions. On the other hand, AIDL and Hamabe, et al.’s approach are developed to pro- duce HDL descriptions. The instruction behav- ior, the timing relations of pipeline stages and the structure of the processor core are described in these languages. Using these languages, HDL descriptions of the target processor can be gen- erated. However, the modification cost is larger than that of other approaches based on proces- 1190
Vol. 44 No. 5 JPEG Encoder Design Space Exploration Using PEAS-III1191sor specification language, because detail infor- mation is described when designers use these languages.The PEAS-III system13)∼15) is one of the ASIP development systems, which generates not only synthesizable HDL descriptions but the target compiler and the target assembler. PEAS-III is based on processor specification language approach. Hence, wide range of processor architecture can be described using the PEAS-III system. The PEAS-III system has well parameterized resource models, Flexi- ble Hardware Models (FHM)16). FHM-DBMS (DataBase Management System) produces the resource specification to generate HDL and the target compiler. When designers would like to change the features of resources, they only change the parameters of FHM. Moreover, de- signers describe processor specification through the PEAS-III input environment using GUIs. Resources and other architecture parameters are specified using GUIs. These features reduce the modification cost and improve design reuse. In this paper, JPEG encoder application, one of the typical DSP applications, was designed using the ASIP design methodology. Instruc- tions for JPEG encoder, such as DCT instruc- tion, and butterfly instructions, were added to the initial design. Area, performance, and execution cycles of processors were calculated using HDL descriptions, compiler, and assem- bler. From experimental results, various archi- tectures can be designed in a short time, and de- signers can select an optimal architecture that matches design constraints.The rest of this paper is organized as fol- lows. In Section 2, SoC design using ASIP is described. In Section 3, the PEAS-III system, one of the ASIP development systems, is intro- duced. The case study and experimental result are discussed in Section 4, and examined in Sec- tion 5. Finally, Section 6 concludes this paper and future work is described.2. SoC Design Using ASIPRequirements of embedded systems such as consumer products, are cost effective architec- ture and low power. Moreover, rapid technol- ogy change makes product life cycles short and makes time-to-market a critical issue for in- dustries. Time required for design and verifi- cation are measured in months or years with high uncertainly. One of the solutions for this requirement is ASIP (Application SpecificOff-the-shelf General Purpose Processor     Fig. 1ASIPASICCost/PerformanceAdvantage of ASIP solution.Instruction-set Processor) solution. ASIP is a programmable processor that is designed for a specific, well-defined class of applications. An ASIP is usually characterized by a small, well- defined instruction-set that is tuned to the crit- ical inner loops of the application code.Figure 1 shows advantage of ASIP solu- tion. The horizontal axis is cost-performance ratio and the vertical axis is flexibility. Off- the-shelf general purpose processor like In- tel Pentium processor has high flexibility, but cost-performance ratio of the general purpose processor is low. On the contrary, although ASIC achieves high cost-performance, ASIC has lower flexibility. The ASIP has higher flexi- bility than ASIC has, and achieves higher cost- performance than the general purpose proces- sor. Hence, ASIP can be one of the key compo- nent of SoCs.On the other hand, the cost of a SoC de- sign is very expensive. Industry analysts make much of the rising cost of deep-submicron IC masks: The cost of a full mask set approaches $1 million. As a result, it is difficult that design- ers change the SoC specification and redevelop chips. ASIP design methods permit painless workarounds for the design cost problem be- cause ASIP has flexibility. Hence, flexibility is a key issue in developing SoC. Although ASIC cannot satisfy flexibility, ASIP can satisfy flex- ibility.In addition, ASIP design methods increase designer productivity. RTL-based ASIC design routinely includes bugs because complexity of ASIC increases. An ASIP based SoC design method significantly cuts risks of fatal logic bugs and permits graceful recovery when testers discover a bug. The reason is that designersFlexibility
1192IPSJ JournalMay 2003   Architecture SpecificationInput EnvironmentBehavior Model HDL DescriptionCycle Accurate Model HDL Desc.Synthesizable HDL DescriptionFig. 2 Overview of PEAS-III system.Hardware Cost Max Frequency Power Execution Cycle   FlexibleHardware Model Management SystemFlexible Hardware Model Behavior Level RT Level Gate Level Layout Level      HDL Generator Software Development Environment Generator             develop software instead of hardware logic in complex function fields.3. ASIP Development System: PEAS- IIIPEAS-III (Practical Environment for ASIP development) is one of the ASIP development systems. PEAS-III has the following features: (1) Synthesizable HDL description generation, (2) Software development environment genera- tion, (3) Design reuse framework based on Flex- ible Hardware Model (FHM), and (4) Design quality estimation at early design phase.The overview of the PEAS-III system is shown in Fig. 2. Processor architecture spec- ification is written in the input environment, which encourages efficient input. The processor specification description includes: (1) architec- ture parameters such as pipeline stage counts, the number of delayed branch slots, (2) decla- ration of resources included in the processor, such as ALUs and register files, (3) instruc- tion format definitions, (4) behavior and micro- operation descriptions of instructions, and (5) interrupt definitions including cause conditions and micro-operation description of interrupts. The architecture description is passed from the input environment to the HDL generator and the software development environment genera- tor. The HDL generator and the compiler gen- erator uses FHM, which is parameterized re- source model. Since FHM is used in HDL and compiler generation, designers can change the characteristics of resource only by changing theparameters of each resource.In the compiler generation method of PEAS-III, special instructions can be added using Compiler-Known-Functions. Compiler-Known- Functions directly replace instructions instead of constructing a usual function call. Designers can tune processors for the target application using Compiler-Known-Functions.It is the advantage of the PEAS-III design that a processor architect can design the syn- thesizable HDL and the target compiler rapidly. Since execution cycles, clock frequency and hardware cost can be evaluated in the early de- sign phase, designers can find an optimal archi- tecture in the short design time.4. Case Study4.1 Objective of Case StudyObjective of this case study is to evaluate ef- fectiveness of ASIP design method and the pro- posed ASIP development environment. Partic- ularly, it is evaluated that design space explo- ration time using the PEAS-III system when designers develop an application system used in real world. Target applications of ASIP include digital signal processing (DSP) such as JPEG, MPEG, network system, wireless communica- tion system such as mobile phone. JPEG is one of the target applications of ASIP, and JPEG is used for a lot of systems such as digital camera, mobile phone with camera, and so on. Hence, JPEG is a good example to confirm effective- ness of ASIP design method and the proposed ASIP development environment.Application Program Compiler Assembler Simulator Debugger  Architecture Information Design Quality EstimatorObject Code Estimation Report
Vol. 44No. 5JPEG Encoder Design Space Exploration Using PEAS-III11938 * 8 blocksSource Image DataFig. 3Step1DCT based EncoderTable Table Specification SpecificationCompressed Image Data              JPEG encoder procedures based on the DCT.Step2MADD3Step3MADD1Step4MADD2S1_16S5_16-1-C1_4C1_4          -C1_4 S1_8C1_8C1_4 C1_4        -S3_8      -1C3_8      -1        -1C1_4 C1_4C1_4    -1-1-1       -1C7_16        x(0) x(1) x(2) x(3) x(4) x(5) x(6) x(7)C1_16X(0)X(4)X(2)X(6)X(1)X(5)X(3)                           ADD2Fig. 4MADD1ADD14.2 Target Application: JPEG CodecJPEG is a definition of a still-image com- pression algorithm established by the JPEG committee. Figure 3 shows JPEG encoder procedures based on the DCT. In the encod- ing process, the input component’s samples are grouped into 8 × 8 blocks, and each block is transformed by the DCT into a set of 64 val- ues referred to as DCT coefficient. The first element is referred to as the DC coefficient and the other elements are referred to as the AC coefficients. Each of the 64 coefficients is then quantized using one of 64 corresponding values from a quantization table. After quantization, the DC coefficient and the 63 AC coefficients are prepared for Variable Length Coding (VLC) which compresses the DC and AC coefficients. In JPEG specification, one of two coding pro- cedures can be used. One is Huffman encoding and the other is arithmetic coding.4.3 Architecture CandidatesSeveral kinds of parameters are defined in JPEG specification. In this case study, 8 bitprecision baseline algorithm was selected. Huff- man coding was selected as VLC and VLD. In the following section, architecture candidates are described, and experimental results are ex- plained.4.3.1 DCT and IDCTDCT and IDCT are designed using ChenDCT algorithm 17) , which is one of the famousalgorithm reducing multiplications and addi-tions. Data flow of Chen DCT is shown inFig. 4. Here, x(i) denotes element of input ma-trix, X (i) denotes transformed element. C i   jand Si j denote cos( i×π ) and sin( i×π ), respec- jjtively. Using Chen algorithm, multiplication times are reduced from 64 to 16, and addition times are reduced from 56 to 26 in 1 dimen- sional 8 points DCT. IDCT can be designed us- ing inverse of DCT. Hence, multiplication and addition times in IDCT are reduced as much as those of DCT.There are several approaches in DCT and IDCT design.DCTQuantizationData flow of Chen DCT (1-dimensional 8 points).VLC  MADD3C5_16 -S3_16          C3_16-S7_16    X(7)   
1194 IPSJ Journal May 2003• Sequential Instructions Approach Sequential instructions approach stands for software design. All of the algorithm is pro- cessed by software.• DCT Instruction ApproachDCT instructions approach stands for hardware unit design. All of the algorithm is processed by hardware.• Butterfly Instructions Approach Butterfly instructions approach stands for design using fine grain instructions. The part of the algorithm is processed by hard- ware, and the other part of the algorithm is processed by software.These approaches have trade-offs between hardware cost and performance.4.3.2 QuantizationIn quantization design, several approaches exist, which is the same as DCT design. Fig- ure 5 shows the C source code of quantization.quantization (short int ∗input, short int ∗output,short int ∗qtable) { short int *inputPtr = input;for ( ; inputPtr < input + 64; inputPtr++ ) { if ( ∗inputPtr > 0 ) {∗output = (∗inputPtr + (∗qtable >> 1)) / ∗qtable;} else {∗output = (∗inputPtr - (∗qtable >> 1)) /∗qtable; }output++; qtable++;From Fig. 5, quantization divides the element by the element of quantization table. Hence, the performance of divider affects the execution cycles of quantization. In this case study, the algorithm of divider was changed.4.4 Input ImageIn this evaluation, a standard image (Fig. 6) was used as an input image. The image size was 256×256 pixels and the sampling factors of each component were as follows: horizontal sampling factors of Y, U, V were 4, 1, 1, and vertical sampling factor were 4, 1, 1, respectively.4.5 DCT/IDCT UnitFigure 7 shows the DCT/IDCT unit that processes 2 dimensional (2-D) 8 points DCT/IDCT. The input and output ports of DCT/IDCT unit consist of as follows: (a) in- put or output 32-bit data bus, (b) input port of 32-bit base address for data read/write, (c) 32-bit data address bus, (d) 1-bit calculation mode signal to change DCT execution or IDCT } }Fig. 5C source code of quantization.DataFig. 6Sample color image (Lenna).Read and Write Data address base address      2 data read/write or 1 data read/writeon 32 bits data bassstart fin       selectoraddress Unit                   reg0             ADD Block1reg1reg2 ADD Block2reg3selectorreg4MADD1reg5MADD2reg6MADD3reg7Controller       Fig. 7DCT/IDCT Unit.
Vol. 44No. 5JPEG Encoder Design Space Exploration Using PEAS-III1195   IdleFirstSecond4 times execution, (e) 1-bit start signal, and (f) 1-bit fin signal. Functional blocks consist of 8blocks: 16-bit internal registers, ADD block1,ADD block2, MADD1, MADD2, MADD3, ad-dress unit, and controller. ADD block1, ADDblock2, MADD1, MADD2, and MADD3 exe-cute part of Chen DCT data flow illustratedin Fig.4. ADD block1 has 4 input ports (in1,in2, in3, in4), and 4 output ports (out1, out2,out3, out4). Each adder calculates using thefollowing equation: out1 = in1 + in2, out2 =in1−in2, out3 = −in3+in4, out4 = in3+in4.ADD block2 has 8 input ports (in1, in2, in3,in4, in5, in6, in7, in8), and 8 output ports (out1,out2, out3, out4, out5, out6, out7, out8). Eachadder calculates using the following equation:out1 = in1+in8, out2 = in2+in7, out3 =in3+in6, out4 = in4+in5, out5 = in4−in5,out6 = in3−in6, out7 = in2−in7, out8 =in1 − in8. MADD1 has 2 input ports (in1,in2) and 2 output ports (out1, out2). MADD1unit calculates using the following equation:cos(1×π )·in4, out2 = sin(5×π )·in2+cos(5×π )· 16 3×π 16 3×π 16start    8 times8 timesIdle Data Read1st Step4th Step2nd StepData Write    Finite state machine of DCT/IDCT unit controller.4 times   3rd Step  Dimenssion 2Fig. 8Dimenssion 1end   in3, out3 = −sin( 16 )·in2+cos( 16 )·in3, out4 = −sin(7×π) · in1 + cos(7×π) · in4, orout1 = in1+in4, out2 = in2+in3, out3 = in2 − in3, out4 = in1 − in4. Each value is cal- culated in 16-bit fixed point arithmetic.Figure 8 shows the finite state machine of DCT/IDCT unit. The finite state machine con- sists of two part. One is 1-D Chen DCT calcu- lation control part, the other is 2-D DCT cal- culation control part. In 2-D part, first step calculates row of matrix and second step cal- culates column of matrix. In each step, 1-D Chen DCT is executed 8 times. In 1-D part, the flow consists of data read, 4 steps execu- tion illustrated in Fig. 4, and data write. The DCT/IDCT unit fetches data from the data memory to the internal registers. When the DCT/IDCT unit fetches data that is from row of matrix, one 16-bit value can be fetched us- ing an address. In column data of matrix, two 16-bit values can be fetched using an address. Hence, the number of memory accesses when the DCT/IDCT unit fetches from row of ma- trix is 8, and the number of memory accesses when the DCT/IDCT unit fetches from column of matrix is 4. From this feature, the number of memory accesses can be reduced when the DCT/IDCT unit is used. The reason why the DCT/IDCT unit has 32-bit data bus is that the data is allocated to the data memory which is the same memory of ASIP.    out1=cos(1×π)·in1+cos(1×π)·in2,out1= 1×π 4 1×π 416 16  cos( 4 )·in1−cos( 4 )·in2. MADD2 has 2  input ports (in1, in2) and 2 output ports (out1,out2). MADD2 unit calculates using the follow-ingequation:out1=sin(1×π)·in1+cos(1×π)· 3×π8 3×π8  in2, out2 = sin( 8 )·in1+cos( 8 )·in2, MADD3 has 4 input ports (in1, in2, in3, in4) and 4 output ports (out1, out2, out3, out4). MADD3 unit can change calculation mode to use the same unit twice in Chen DCT/IDCT calculation flow. MADD3 unit calculates using  the following equation: out1 = sin( 1×π ) · in1 + 16 
1196IPSJ Journal May 2003(a) Behavior Description for Compiler Generatorckf prototype {void dct ( unsigned int , unsigned int );(a) Behavior Description for Compiler Generator ckf prototype {void madd1 ( unsigned int , unsigned int );}}DCT { operand {GPR UInt31to0 a;GPR UInt31to0 b;}}format { “DCT” “,” a “,” b } function {stage(1) { PC.read IMEM.load wordPC.inc IR.read }stage(2) {GPR.read0 GPR.read1 }stage(3) { }stage(4) { DCT0.dct }stage(5) { } }}behavior { behavior {(b) Micro-Operation Descriptionstage(1){ IR := IMEM[PC]; PC.inc();},stage(2){ $op1 := GPR.read0(rs); $op2 := GPR.read1(rt);}, stage(3){},stage(4){$dummy := DCT0.dct($op1,$op2);},stage(5){}(c) Bit FieldFig. 9 DCT instruction specification of PEAS-III.4.6 Additional Instructions • DCTDCT instruction executes the procedure of DCT. This instruction uses the DCT unit described in section 4.5. Instruction set specification for PEAS-III is described in Fig.9. In application written in C lan- guage, DCT is described using function call. In PEAS-III specification, Compiler- Known-Function “dct” is defined, and the behavior of DCT instruction is defined us- ing “dct” function. Micro-Operation de- scription defines pipeline execution. DCT unit is executed at pipeline stage 4.• MADD1MADD1 instruction calculates the MADD1 block in Fig. 4. MADD1 instruction takes 2 operands as input and write back to the same operand registers. Instruction set specification for PEAS-III is described in Fig. 10. In application written in C lan- guage, MADD1 is described using function call. In PEAS-III specification, Compiler- Known-Function “madd1” is defined, and the behavior of MADD1 instruction is de- fined using “madd1” function. MADD1 unit is executed at pipeline stage 3.• MADD2MADD2 instruction calculates the MADD2 block in Fig. 4. MADD2 instruction takes 2 operands as input and write back to the same operand registers. Instruction set specification for PEAS-III is described in(b) Micro-Operation Descriptionstage(1){ IR := IMEM[PC]; PC.inc();},stage(2){ $op1 := GPR.read0(rs); $op2 := GPR.read1(rt);}, stage(3){($result1, $result2) := MADD1U0.madd($op1, $op2);}, stage(4){ },stage(5){GPR.write0($result1, rs); GPR.write1($result2, rt); }(c) Bit FieldFig. 10 MADD1 instruction specification of PEAS-III.(a) Behavior Description for Compiler Generatorckf prototype {void madd2 ( unsigned int , unsigned int );}MADD2 { operand {GPR UInt15to0 a; GPR UInt15to0 b;}format { “MADD2” “,” a “,” b } function {stage(1) { PC.read IMEM.load wordPC.inc IR.read }stage(2) {GPR.read0 GPR.read1 } stage(3) {MADD2U0.madd } stage(4) { }stage(5) {GPR.write0 GPR.write1} }behavior {madd2 ( a , b );} }(b) Micro-Operation Descriptionstage(1){ IR := IMEM[PC]; PC.inc();},stage(2){ $op1 := GPR.read0(rs); $op2 := GPR.read1(rt);}, stage(3){($result1, $result2) := MADD2U0.madd($op1, $op2);}, stage(4){ },stage(5){GPR.write0($result1, rs); GPR.write1($result2, rt);}MADD1 { operand {GPR UInt15to0 a; GPR UInt15to0 b;format { “MADD1” “,” a “,” b } function {stage(1) { PC.read IMEM.load word  dct ( a , b );}} }}madd1 ( a , b );PC.inc IR.read }stage(2) {GPR.read0 GPR.read1 } stage(3) {MADD1U0.madd } stage(4) { }stage(5) {GPR.write0 GPR.write1 } 000000 rs  rt0000000000  111111  000000 rs  rt0000000000  011110    (c) Bit FieldFig. 11MADD2 instruction specification of PEAS-III. 000000 rs  rt0000000000  011111  Fig. 11. In application written in C lan- guage, MADD2 is described using function call. In PEAS-III specification, Compiler- Known-Function “madd2” is defined, and the behavior of MADD2 instruction is de- fined using “madd2” function. MADD2 unit is executed at pipeline stage 3.4.7 Compiler Generation for Target ProcessorsThe target compiler is generated using pro-
Vol. 44No. 5 JPEG Encoder Design Space Exploration Using PEAS-III 1197Table 11. Normal 2. Normal 3. Normal 4. Normal 5. Butterfly 6. Butterfly 7. Butterfly 8. Butterfly 9. DCT10. DCT 11. DCT 12. DCTProcessor cores and their execution cycles of JPEG application.  Multiplier   Divider   Area(K gates)  Max Freq. (MHz)  Exec Cycles (M cycles)  seq(32) seq(32) array array     seq(34) array seq(34) array       39.43 52.1 57.59 70.19    151 22.544.5 43.3    61.28 51.19 44.54 34.45    seq(32) seq(32) array array     seq(34) array seq(34) array       57.3 70.0 75.5 88.0    149 23.044.5 23.0    53.57 43.48 43.52 33.43    seq(32) seq(32) array array     seq(34) array seq(34) array       71.17 89.35 83.86101.93    151 22.443.3 43.3    39.62 29.53 36.25 26.17        cessor specification partly represented in previ- ous section. The target compiler produced by the proposed compiler generator executes the following steps: (1) Parsing the source code, (2) Machine independent optimization, (3) Syn- tax tree rewriting and pattern matching, (4) Register allocation and Spill code insertion, (5) Instruction scheduling, (6) Machine depen- dent optimization, and (7) Output assembly code. When special instructions such as DCT, MADD1 and so on are added to the processor specification, the proposed compiler generation method produces the following information: (a) function prototypes for C parser, (b) mapping rules for special instructions, and (c) instruc- tion throughput and latency table for instruc- tion scheduling. When parser reads the special instructions written in target application, the generated compiler makes CKF internal repre- sentation for compiler. When back-end of com- piler generates assembler, target instruction is emitted using mapping rule for CKF. For exam- ple, DCT function is read by the compiler and the internal representation “xirCKF” is gener- ated, which means that extended internal repre- sentation “CKF”. The “xirCKF” has attributes that include operands and CKF ID. The map- ping rule for “xirCKF” specifies assembly for- mat which is specified in format section. For instance, in DCT instruction in Fig. 9, the map- ping rule of DCT instruction includes instruc- tion string “DCT” and the operand order of DCT instruction “a” and “b”. Furthermore, in- struction latency and throughput are calculated using resource usage described in function sec- tion of instruction behavior specification. Re- source throughput and latency can be obtained from FHM-DBMS. The proposed compiler gen- erator traces the resource connection graph andPower (mW/MHz)2.40 2.44 2.48 2.53 2.48 2.52 2.56 2.61 2.49 2.54 2.58 2.62Library: 0.14 CMOS Standard Cell Library.calculates instruction throughput and latency.4.8 How to Estimate Design QualityHardware Cost and maximum clock fre- quency were estimated using Synopsys De- sign Compiler. Input of Design Compiler was synthesizable HDL generated by PEAS-III. 0.14 μm CMOS standard cell library (voltage 1.5 V) was used for logic synthesis. Execution cycle was estimated using Synopsys Scirocco that is a cycle-based HDL simulator. Dynamic power was estimated by gate-level simulation using Mentor Graphics ModelSim and Synop- sys Power Compiler.4.9 Processor OrganizationProcessor organization in this case study is shown in Table 1. Normal denotes base in- struction set that is sub set of MIPS-R3000 instruction set. Butterfly denotes instruction set added MADD1, and MADD2 instructions. DCT denotes instruction set added DCT in- struction. The hardware algorithm of multi- plier is sequential type that executes 32 cycles and array type that executes 1 cycle. On the other hand, the hardware algorithm of divider is sequential type that executes 34 cycles, and array type that executes 1 cycle.4.10 Trade-offs Between Hardware Cost and PerformanceFigure 12 shows trade-offs between hard- ware cost and execution cycles when JPEG encoder has been executed. Horizontal axis is hardware cost, and vertical axis is execu- tion cycles. The number of each plot point in Fig. 12 corresponds to each processor in Table 1. From Fig. 12, the trade-off between hardware cost and execution cycles exists when instruc- tions are added and the hardware algorithms are changed.Figures 13 and 14 show trade-offs between
1198IPSJ JournalMay 2003  Fig. 12Trade-offs between hardware cost and execu- tion cycles when JPEG encoder was executed.Fig. 15Trade-offs between hardware cost and power consumption when JPEG encoder was exe- cuted within 0.5 second.  Fig. 13Trade-offs between hardware cost and execu- tion time when JPEG encoder was executed (66 MHz).Fig. 16Trade-offs between hardware cost and power consumption when JPEG encoder was exe- cuted within 1 second. Fig. 14Trade-offs between hardware cost and execu- tion time when JPEG encoder was executed (40 MHz).show that designers have to consider not only the execution cycles of an application, but also the clock frequency when architecture candi- dates are selected. In Fig.13, when a design constraint is that hardware cost is under 60 K gates, the processor No.5 in Table 1 is selected as the optimal architecture.4.11 Trade-offs Between Hardware Cost and Power ConsumptionFigures 15 and 16 show trade-offs between hardware cost and power consumption when JPEG encoder has been executed. The hori- zontal axis is hardware cost, and the vertical axis is dynamic power. In Fig.15, JPEG En- coder was executed within 0.5 second, and in Fig.16, JPEG Encoder was executed within 1 second. In Fig.15, the frequency of processor 1 was about 120MHz, the frequency of pro- cessor 9 was about 90MHz. Hence, the dy- namic power of processor 1 in Fig. 15 was about 290mW, and the dynamic power of processor 9 was about 190mW. If design constraint of power consumption is 200 mW, the processor 9 can be selected, but if design constraint of power consumption is 300 mW, processor 1 can be selected because the hardware cost of pro-hardware cost and execution time when JPEG encoder has been executed. Horizontal axis is hardware cost, and vertical axis is execution time. In Fig. 13, execution time was calculated using execution cycles and clock frequency that was 66 MHz, and in Fig. 14, execution time was calculated using execution cycles and clock fre- quency that was 40MHz. As shown in these figures, the number of architecture candidates was changed because the max clock frequency of each architecture candidate ranges between about 20 MHz and 150 MHz. These results
Vol. 44 No. 5 JPEG Encoder Design Space Exploration Using PEAS-III 1199Table 2 Design time.When an application such as DSP applica- tion is designed using ASIPs, designers con- sider trade-offs among hardware cost, perfor- mance and power consumption. Generally, it is said that the design time of hardware de- scription, compiler and assembler require sev- eral months or at least several weeks. How- ever, it is too long to meet a requirement of the design time in design space exploration. On the other hand, when designers use other ASIP development systems that have been ex- plained in section 1, either software develop- ment environment or hardware description is produced in a short time, but the other part, for example processor cores for software develop- ment environment, must be developed by them- selves. The advantage of the PEAS-III system is that compiler, assembler and hardware de- scription are generated at the same time. Fur- thermore, the modification cost of the design is low, and hardware modules such as DCT unit can be reused easily, because designers only se- lect modules from FHM-DBMS as resources. Using the PEAS-III system, designers can eval- uate processors and select an optimal architec- ture in a short design time.The architecture candidates described in Sec- tion 4.3 were selected from the feature of C source code or data flow. Although a lot of can- didates can be considered, several architecture candidates that were expected to improve pro- cessor performance were designed to evaluate the potential of PEAS-III design method in this case study. Generally, architecture candidates selection is very difficult. Hence, the profiling environment to select architecture candidates and architecture selection method are needed to reduce design cost and to get better solution.In Table 2, the time of others includes debug time and simulation time of target processor. To reduce this part, a source code debugger and a faster simulator are desirable.6. ConclusionIn this paper, JPEG encoder design space exploration using the PEAS-III system is de- scribed, which is one of the ASIP develop- ment system. Instructions for JPEG encoder, such as DCT instruction, and butterfly instruc- tions, were added to the initial processor. Area, performance, and dynamic power of processors were calculated using the generated HDL de- scription, compiler, and assembler. From ex- perimental results, 12 architectures can be de-  Time (hour) 1301 0.1164.1  C source code designDCT unit design 60 Total 190 Base processor design 12 Registration of DCT unit and Convo- 1 lution blocks to FHM-DBMSInstruction additionHardware algorithm selectionOthers 150            Total cessor 1 is smaller than that of processor 9. Furthermore, if design constraint of execu- tion time is within 1 second, the trade-off be- tween hardware cost and power consumption is Fig. 16. In Fig. 16, processors 5 and 7 cannotbe architecture candidates.4.12 Design TimeThe design time of the case study is shown in Table 2. From Table 2, about ten hours were spent using the PEAS-III system. Here, the reason why the hardware algorithm selection time is short is only changing FHM parameters to select hardware algorithm. From this result, the hardware description and the target com- piler can be designed in a short design time. 130 hours were spent designing JPEG codec using C source code. 60 hours were spent DCT unit design. Others include debug time and simula- tion time and synthesizing time to evaluate the processor core. It seems that the time of JPEG codec application design and DCT unit design is as long as other environments.5. DiscussionThe experimental result shows that architec- ture candidates are changed when clock fre- quency or time constraint are changed. From this result, designers must consider not only the execution cycles of a target processor but also the max frequency of a target proces- sor and power consumption. For example, in Fig. 15, processor 5 can be an architecture can- didate. However, in Fig.16, processor 5 is not an architecture candidate because processor 3 can achieve low power and the same hardware cost. In the PEAS-III design, software devel- opment environment and designed processor’s HDL descriptions are generated at the same time. Hence, designers can consider the execu- tion cycles of application, the clock frequency of processor, hardware cost and power consump- tion efficiently.
1200 IPSJ Journal May 2003signed in a short time. Moreover, the design quality of each processor including hardware cost, execution cycles of application, clock fre- quency, and power consumption was evaluated using the PEAS-III system efficiently. Future work includes instruction set simulator, profiler, and debugger generation, and architecture can- didates selection method.Acknowledgments The authors are grate- ful to the members of PEAS Project. The authors also would like to express thanks to Mr. Nobuyuki Hikichi from SRA (Software Re- search Associates Inc.). Moreover, the authors are also grateful to Japan Novel Corp. The compiler development kit CoSy is provided by ACE Associated Compiler Experts bv. This work was partly supported by STARC (Semi- conductor Technology Academic Research Cen- ter), and one of tools was supported by Mentor Graphics higher education program.References1) Sato, J., Alomary, A.Y., Honma, Y., Nakano, T., Shiomi, A., Hikichi, N. and Imai, M.: PEAS-I: A Hardware/Software Codesign Sys- tem for ASIP Development, IEICE Trans. Fundamentals, Vol.E77-A, No.3, pp.483–491 (March 1994).2) Shackleford, B., Yasuda, M., Okushi, E., Koizumi, H., Tomiyama, H. and Yasuura, H.: Satsuki: An Integrated Processor Synthesis and Compiler Generation System, IEICE Trans. Inf. & Syst., Vol.E79-D, No.10, pp.1373–1381 (Oct. 1996).3) Yang, J.-H., Kim, B.-W., Nam, S.-J., Cho, J.- H., Seo, S.-W., Ryu, C.-H., et al.: MetaCore: An Application Specific DSP Development Sys- tem, 35th DAC, pp.800–803 (1998).4) Campasano, R. and Wilberg, J.: Embedded System Design, Design Automation for Embed- ded Systems, Vol.1, No.1-2, pp.5–50 (Jan.1996).5) Tensilica: Xtensa. http://www.tensilica.com 6) Fauth, A.: Beyond tool-specific machine de- scriptions, Code Generation for Embedded Pro- cessors, pp.138–152, Kluwer Academic Pub-lishers (1995).7) Hadjiyiannis,G.,Russo,P.andDevadas,S.:AMethodology for Accurate Performance Eval- uation in Architecture Exploration, 36th De- sign Automation Conference, pp.927–932 (June 1999).8) Pees, S., Hoffmann, A., Zivojnovic, V. and Meyr, H.: LISA — Machine Description Lan- guage for Cycle-Accurate Models of Pro- grammable DSP Architecture, 36th Design Au- tomation Conference, pp.933–938 (1999).9) Paulin, P.G., Liem, C., May, T.C. and Sutawala, S.: FlexWare: A Flexible Firmware Development Environment for Embedded Sys- tems, Code Generation for Embedded Proces- sors, pp.65–84 (1995).10) Halambi, A., Grun, P., Ganesh, V., Khare, A., Dutt, N. and Nicolau, A.: EXPRESSION: A Language for Architecture Exploration through Compiler/Simulator Retargetability, DATE 99, pp.485–490 (March 1999).11) Morimoto, T., Saito, K., Nakamura, H., Boku, T. and Nakazawa, K.: Advanced Processor Design Using Hardware Description Language AIDL, ASP-DAC’97, pp.387–390 (1997).12) Hamabe, M., Nose, A., Togawa, N., Yanagi- sawa, M. and Ohtsuki, T.: A Generation Sys- tem for Hardware Description of Pipelined Pro- cessors, Tech. Report of IEICE, VLD97-117, pp.33–40 (1997) (in japanese).13) Itoh, M., Higaki, S., Sato, J., Shiomi, A., Takeuchi, Y., Kita jima, A. and Imai, M.: PEAS–III: An ASIP design environment, Proc. 2000 IEEE International Conference on Com- puter Design: VLSI in Computers & Processors (ICCD2000), pp.430–436 (Sept. 2000).14) Kobayashi, S., Mita, K., Takeuchi, Y. and Imai, M.: Design Space Exploration for DSP Applications using the ASIP Development Sys- tem PEAS-III, Proc. IEEE International Con- ference on Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Pro- cessing, Vol.3, pp.3168–3171 (May 2002).15) Kobayashi, S., Takeuchi, Y., Kitajima, A. and Imai, M.: Compiler Generation in PEAS-III: an ASIP Development System, SCOPES 2001, St. Goal, Germany (March 2001).16) Takeuchi, Y., Ueda, K., Yamane, Y., Shiomi, A. and Imai, M.: Flexible Hardware Model: A Hardware Model for IP Reuse and its Database Management System FHM-DBMS, Technical Report of IEICE, Vol.VLD2002-119, pp.221– 226 (Nov. 2002) (in japanese).17) Chen, W.H., Smith, C.H. and Fralick, S.C.: A fast computational algorithm for the dis- crete cosine transform, IEEE Trans. Commun., Vol.COM-25, pp.1004–1009 (Sept. 1977).(Received October 16, 2002) (Accepted March 4, 2003)
Vol. 44No. 5JPEG Encoder Design Space Exploration Using PEAS-III 1201Shinsuke Kobayashi re- ceived his M.E. degree from Os- aka University in 2000. He is currently a doctoral candidate in the Department of Informat- ics and Mathematical Sciences, Graduate School of EngineeringScience at Osaka University. His research inter- ests include software development environment generation for ASIPs, VLSI design, processor architecture and VLSI CAD. He is a member of IEEE CAS Society, ACM SIGDA, and IE- ICE.Kentaro Mita received his B.E. degree from Osaka Uni- versity in 2001. He is cur- rently a master’s candidate in the Department of Informat- ics and Mathematical Sciences, Graduate School of EngineeringScience at Osaka University. His research inter- ests include software development environment generation for ASIPs.Yoshinori Takeuchi received his B.E., M.E. and Dr. Eng. degrees from Tokyo Institute of Technology in 1987, 1989 and 1992, respectively. He is cur- rently an Associate Professor of the Graduate School of Engi-neering Science at Osaka University. His re- search interests include digital signal process- ing, VLSI design and VLSI CAD. He is a mem- ber of IEEE of SP, CAS, and SSC Society, and IEICE.Masaharu Imai received his B.S., M.S., and Ph.D. de- grees from Nagoya University, Nagoya, Japan in 1974, 1976, and 1979, respectively. He joined the Department of Infor- mation and Computer Sciencesat Toyohashi University of Technology in 1979. He was a visiting Assistant Professor at the Uni- versity of South Carolina, SC, U.S.A. from 1984 to 1985. Since 1996, he has been with the De- partment of Informatics and Mathematical Sci- ence, Graduate School of Engineering Science, Osaka University, where he is currently a pro- fessor. Since 1991, he has been working for the Standardization of VHDL under IEEE/DASC and EIAJ (Electronic Industries Association of Japan). His research interests include HW/SW Codesign and VLSI architecture. He is a mem- ber of IEICE of Japan, IPSJ, IEEE, and ACM.     