Vol. 44 No. 6 IPSJ Journal June 2003Recommended PaperNotification of Certificate Revocation Status between Different Domains under a PKI SystemYutaka Miyake,† Jonathan K. Millen,†† Grit Denker,†† Toshiaki Tanaka† and Koji Nakao†When public key certificates are used to control access by a client in one domain to a server in another domain, the certificate revocation status should be distributed to the server domain too. For security reasons, the distribution of information to other domains should be minimized, and external distribution points are subject to attack from third parties on the Internet. In this paper, we propose a mechanism to convey the current revocation status of certificates to other domains securely under PKI (Public Key Infrastructure) system in WWW environment. Because our proposal does not need to modify the standard browsers, we can introduce the proposed method to the current WWW environment easily. We implemented prototype system of our proposal, and evaluated the system to prove the effectiveness of this system.1. IntroductionThe combination of WWW (World Wide Web) browsers and servers makes it convenient for anyone to access information on servers. Some servers provide private or sensitive infor- mation and require users to log in with pass- word or smart cards. This form of access con- trol is suitable if users must be distinguished from one another.Recently, many organizations have been in- troducing PKI (Public Key Infrastructure) and distribute public key certificates for each mem- ber. The certificate includes user information, a public key for the user, and a signature by the CA (Certification Authority). If the CA is trustworthy and it is proved that a user has a private key that corresponds to the public key in the certificate, the user can be identified and authenticated.It is possible to use the PKI system for ac- cess control. In case of WWW accessing, Web servers can identify the accessing clients by checking their certificates and possession of pri- vate keys. This method has several advan- tages compared with systems with passwords or smart cards. The main difference between the PKI and password-based system is the pro- cedure after the password or private key is com- promised. In case of password-based access con- trol, the client should change the password for every Web server. If the client accesses many† KDDI R&D Laboratories Inc. †† SRI International Inc.Web servers with the same password, this pro- cedure will be required for each Web server. Though the clients may assign different pass- words for each Web server, this method neces- sitates troublesome password management. In the case of PKI, when the private key is re- vealed, the client revokes the certificate corre- sponding to the private key, and asks the CA to issue a new certificate. It is not necessary to inform every Web server that the private key and certificate are altered, because the Web servers obtain this revoked status information when they validate the certificate of accessing clients. Even if someone attempted to use the old certificate, when the revocation status of the certificate is checked, it is proved that the certificate is invalid.In order to incorporate the PKI system into access control, the server has to have the ca- pability to validate the certificates of clients. Normally, the server checks the revocation sta- tus of a certificate by retrieving a CRL (Cer- tificate Revocation List) 1),2) or accessing an OCSP (Online Certificate Status Protocol) 3) responder. If the client and server belong to same domain and their certificates are issued by a CA in this domain, it is easy for the server to check the status of client’s certificate. How- ever if the client and server belong to differ- ent domains and their CAs are managed inde-The initial version of this paper was presented at CSEC Workshop on July 2001, which was sponsored by SIGCSEC. This paper was recommended to be submitted to the Journal of IPSJ by the chairperson of SIGCSEC.  1604
 Vol. 44 No. 6 Notification of Certificate Revocation Status between Different Domains1605pendently, a mechanism to inform the server in the other domain of the status of the certificate should be provided.In this paper, we discuss the notification method for conveying the status of certificates between different domains for WWW environ- ment. In this situation, both domains rely on their own root CA and there may be some re- strictions to access resource servers on the other domain. Therefore we propose an appropriate procedure to exchange the status of certificates safely. In the proposed procedure, when the client accesses the server, the client side sends the revocation status of client certificate to the server domain. Therefore, the server domain can have revocation status of clients as recent as possible in access always. Moreover, the proposed procedure can be introduced to the WWW environment easily without any modi- fications of browser software. We have imple- mented prototype system of our proposal, and evaluated the system to confirm that the pro- cedure is compatible with the current WWW environment.The rest of this paper is organized as follows: In the next section, we describe the procedure of notification to inform the revoked certificate status between different domains. In Section 3, we propose the procedure of notification be- tween different domains for the WWW environ- ment. In Section 4, we explain the implementa- tion of prototype system. Section 5 discuss the proposed procedure, and conclusions are pre- sented in Section 6.2. Notification of Revoked Certificate Status between Different Domains2.1 Connect of Two Independent PKI Domains by Cross CertificatesIn order to construct a certificate chain from a client certificate to a CA in server domain, both the CA that issues the client certificate and the CA in server domain would normally have a same root CA at the top of the CA hier- archy. Generally, the certificate chain is made via the root CA. However, many domains man- age their own root-CA independently. In this case, another method is needed to establish a certificate chain between different domains.Cross certificates 4) have been introduced to resolve this problem. Figure 1 shows the mechanism of cross certificates. In this figure, there are two domains, Domain C for client side and Domain S for server side. Domain C andCA-C (Root CA)Certificate Issuance (2)Certificate-CClientDomain C (Client Side)Cross Certificates (1)(5)(3)Certificate-CCA-S (Root CA)Validity (4) RequestServerDomain S (Server Side)Revocation status checkFig. 1 Certificate validation using cross certificates.Domain S have their own root CA, CA-C and CA-S respectively. In the environment of cross certificates, CA-C and CA-S exchange their public key certificates and sign the received cer- tificates. This means that the server that re- lies on CA-S can accept certificates signed by CA-C, because there is a certificate for CA-C signed by CA-S. In this situation, the server in Domain S can validate the certificate of client (Certificate-C) with the following procedure. (1) The root-CAs in Domain C (CA-C) andDomain S (CA-S) exchange their public key certificates. The received certificates are signed by each root-CA.(2) The CA-C in Domain C issues a public key certificate for a client (Certificate-C). This certificate is signed by the CA-C.(3) When the client accesses a server in Do- main S, it sends its public key certificate (Certificate-C) to the server.(4) The server checks the validity period and signature in the certificate. If the sig- nature of this certificate is signed by the CA-C, the server needs to retrieve the certificate for CA-C. Therefore the server retrieves the cross certificate for CA-C, and checks its signature. Because the cross certificate for CA-C is signed by the reliable CA (CA-S), the server can rely on it. If the certificate (Certificate- C) is signed by a public key in the certifi- cate for CA-C, it is deemed conditionally valid.
1606 IPSJ Journal June 20032.2 Check of Revocation Status for Certificates between Different Do- mainsThe sever can validate certificates issued by CAs in other domains by using the cross cer- tificates. After validating the signature in cer- tificate, the server should check the revocation status of the client certificate ((5) in Fig. 1). If the client certificate is revoked before it expires, the certificate becomes unavailable.In order to get the revocation information for certificates, the server should retrieve a CRL 1),2) that is a list of revoked certificates, or should access an online verification server, such as an OCSP responder3). In case of the CRL, the server requires the CRL that was issued by the same CA that issued the client certificate. The online verification server also needs the in- formation from the CA that issued the client certificate. Therefore the server has to access another domain to retrieve the revocation in- formation for the client certificate if the CA in another domain issued it.When the server retrieves the CRL from an- other domain or accesses the online verification server in another domain, there are some prob- lems.• Each domain must prepare an access point that provides certificate status informa- tion outside of the firewall for other do- mains. Because the access point can be accessed from other domains, maximum se- curity protection is required for its data.• Access to the access point should be re- stricted to known, registered domains. The access point should not send information about its domain to unrelated domains.• The access point should provide only the information that is required to access other domains. Outflow of unnecessary informa- tion may reveal the organizational struc- ture in its domain, and it may become a security hole.These problems also increase the manage- ment cost for each domain, and increase the risk of intrusion from other domains by placing the access point outside of the firewall.2.3 Push Mechanism for Notification of Revoked StatusBecause it is not safe to make an external access point for other domains, we use a push mechanism for notification of revoked status. This means that the client domain sends the status information directly to the other do-mains that need this information directly.As a notification method of the revoked cer- tificate status, we rejected the approach in which each domain distributes CRLs to other registered domains periodically. This methodhas the following disadvantages.Lack of scalability: The CRL informationthat should be sent to other domains in- creases along with the number of registered domains. If there are many registered do- mains that need CRLs, this method re- quires a high speed network.Useless information: The CRL lists the se- rial number of all revoked certificates. However most of this information may not be used at the other domains. It may mean that useless information is sent to many do- mains periodically.Information leak: Since the CRL includes every serial number of revoked certificates, a change in this information may suggest management policy of the PKI, organiza- tional restructuring, etc., in that domain. Therefore each domain should keep to a minimum the information sent to other do- mains.In order to resolve these problems, we pro- pose the mechanism shown in Fig.2. In this mechanism, the client sends a ticket that has the status of the client’s certificate. The proce- dure for this mechanism is as follows.(1) Root CAs in Domain C (CA-C) and Do- main S (CA-S) exchange their public key certificates. The received certificates are signed by each root CA.(2) The CA-C in Domain C issues a public key certificate for a client (Certificate-C).    Ticket for revocation statusTicket(3)Certificate IssuanceCertificate-CClientCross Certificates (1)(4)Ticket Certificate-CCA-C (Root CA)CA-S (Root CA)Validity (5) RequestServerDomain S (Server Side)            (2)                                             Domain C (Client Side)Fig. 2 Transfer of revoked status information with ticket.
Vol. 44 No. 6 Notification of Certificate Revocation Status between Different Domains1607This certificate is signed by the CA-C.(3) Just before accessing a server in Domain S, the client requests a ticket that certi- fies the non-revoked status of client’s cer- tificate by the CA-C. The validity periodof this ticket is short.(4) When the client accesses the server inDomain S, it sends both its public key certificate (Certificate-C) and the ticket to the server.(5) The server checks the conditional validity of the certificate as before. It also checks the signature of the received ticket with same process. If the ticket is not expired and it indicates that the certificate has not been revoked, the certificate is ac- cepted as valid.Only the minimum amount of information is sent to the another domain in this mechanism. Since the ticket that includes the status infor- mation is sent with the certificate, the client can also know the time and domain where the status of the client certificate is sent.3. Adaptation to WWW EnvironmentIn order to apply our proposed approach to practical WWW environment, some modifica- tion and additional elements are required. In this section, we describe system architecture that incorporates our approach in the WWW environment with PKI.3.1 AssumptionsCurrently, browsers and servers for WWW are used widely. Therefore, it is desirable that the current system (browsers, Web servers, CA for PKI) can be used continuously. Accord- ingly, we designed the system architecture in consideration of the following points.• There are several kinds of browsers. We would not like to modify each browser one by one. Moreover, we would not like to distribute special software to each client for this system. Therefore, we do not cus- tomize the client browser for this system.• It is not easy to add new functions to a CA. Therefore, we decide to make a sepa- rate software module called a PGS (Priv- ilege Granting Server). The function of this software is to issue the ticket that indi- cates the status information of a certificate. Since the ticket is signed with the private key of CA, we assume that the PGS is ex- ecuted in same computer on which the CA is running.CA-C / PGS (Root CA)(2)Certificate Certificate-C IssuanceTicketWeb ProxyCross Certificates (1)CA-S (Root CA)Validity (6) RequestWeb ServerDomain S (Server Side)      (4) Ticket for revocationstaus                                         (3)(3)'TicketCertificate-C(5)                      Client (Browser)Domain C (Client Side)Fig. 3• SSL (Securecapability that the server can authorize the client by using the client’s certificate (SSL Handshake Protocol). Because many browsers and Web servers support SSL, we decided to use this function for our system.3.2 System ArchitectureFigure 3 shows the system architecture that incorporates our method. We adopted Web proxy design for ticket handling. When the client browser uses the Web proxy to access the Web server, the Web proxy obtains a ticket and transfers it to the server. The procedure for this architecture is as follows.(1) Root CAs in Domain C (CA-C) and Do- main S (CA-S) exchange their public key certificates. The received certificates are signed by each root-CA.(2) CA-C in Domain C issues a public key certificate for a client (Certificate-C). This certificate is signed by CA-C.(3) The client browser tries to access the Web server in Domain S via the Web proxy in Domain C. The Web proxy re- lays communication between the browser and Web server.(4) During SSL handshake, the Web proxy extracts the certificate information sent by the client. The Web proxy requests the status of the certificate from the CA- C/PGS, and receives the ticket.(5) The Web proxy sends the ticket to the Web server in Domain S. This action is independent of communication between the browser and Web server.(6) The server checks the validity periods and signatures in the certificate and ticket as before.A new Web proxy and some modification ofSystem architecture.Socket Layer) 5),6) has the
1608IPSJ JournalJune 2003     CA CA-C / PGSCertificate-CClient (Browser)PGS(3)Ticket RequestWeb ProxyResult (Accept or Deny)(8)Authorization        (4) Ticket(1) CertificateRequest(2) ClientCertificateCheck(7) Revocation       Status                                   (5) ChangeCipherSpec          (6) Finished          (9) Data Sequence                                    Domain C (Client Side)Fig. 4SSLWeb ServerDomain S (Server Side)the Web server are required in this architecture. However, there is no modification of the client browser because the Web proxy executes the additional procedure instead of the client. The Web proxy might run on the client workstation, or it might run on a gateway so that it can be shared by all the clients on a local network.3.3 Protocol for Authorization and TicketFigure 4 shows the protocol for client au- thorization. (The steps that do not relate to client authorization are omitted in this figure.) SSL handshake protocol messages are shown in italics.(1) In the SSL handshake protocol, the Web server requests the public key certificate of the client by using SSL CertificateRequest message.(2) The client returns the certificate by using the SSL ClientCertificate message.(3) The Web proxy in Domain C ex-tracts the certificate from the message ClientCertificate. It asks the PGS to is- sue the ticket for this certificate.(4) After the Web proxy receives the ticket from the PGS, it transfers the ticket to the Web server in Domain S. The au- thorization module in the Web server re- ceives this ticket. This communication is independent from the SSL handshake protocol. The authorization module is a new function added to the web server to validate and read the ticket.(5) Both the browser and Web server send the ChangeCipherSpec message. After this message, all messages are encrypted.(6) Both the browser and Web server send the Finished message. This message completes the SSL handshake protocol.(7) When the Web server receives the Finished message from the browser, it checks the revoked status of certificate by contacting the authorization module. This check takes the place of other activ- ities like password checking that are per- formed in other servers to control client access.(8) The SSL module in the Web server re- ceives the result (Accept or Deny) of re- vocation status from the authorization module.(9) If the result is Accept, data on accessing pages are transferred to the browser. In case that result is Deny, messages that in- dicate access denial are sent to the client.The Web server does not alter the communi- cation sequence between the server and client. It observes the SSL message passively to ob- tain the client certificate. It does not know any private key or decrypt any encrypted messages. Therefore the secret or authenticated commu- nication between client and server is protected from the Web proxy after the SSL handshake is established.The ticket uses the OCSP Response Message format 3) . Minimally the following informationProtocol for client authorization.      
Vol. 44 No. 6 Notification of Certificate Revocation Status between Different Domains 1609has to be included in this ticket.• CA Name• Serial Number of Client Certificate• Revocation Status (Revoked, Not Revoked,Unknown)• Validity Period of This Ticket• Signature by CA4. Implementation of Prototype Sys- temWe have implemented the proposed architec- ture as prototype system. Three components (Web server, PGS and proxy) are developed for this system. In this section, we describe the outline of these components.4.1 Design PolicyIn order to realize easy adaptation to cur- rent WWW environment, we have considered the following issues to design each component.• As described in Section 3.2, our proposal needs to modify the Web server. Because the program of Web server may be up- graded for correcting security holes and adding new functions, the modification for proposed mechanism should be embedded easily even if the Web server would be up- graded.• Because almost browsers can specify the proxy server by protocol, the Web proxy does not need to support all protocols used by the browsers. So we have decided to im- plement https protocol (HTTP with SSL) only for the proxy. In this case, because other protocols, such as http and ftp, does not pass the proxy, we do not need to sup- port these protocols in the proxy.4.2 Web ServerFor the server side, we chose the Apache HTTP server software and Tomcat as an engine to enable the use of servlets and Java Server Pages (JSPs) with Apache. Apache is built and installed simultaneously with mod ssl, the Apache interfaces to OpenSSL toolkit that sup- ports the SSL and TLS protocols5),6).The authorization server is just another ser- vice of the Web server, implemented as a Java servlet. The servlets are associated with pro- tected Web pages. Each one is an instance of a Java class that performs an access-control check when the page is requested through the Web server. The authorization server accepts tick- ets from the proxy, and it also handles requests from a servlet to confirm that a client certifi- cate has not been revoked. Because this serviceis implemented as servelet, we can adapt this component to the program easily even if the program of Web server is upgraded.The servlets control access to the protected Web pages by making three checks:• the client certificate is properly signed and not expired;• there is a ticket providing that the client certificate has not been revoked; and• there is and ACL (Access Control List) en- try (in .xdaaccess file) specifying the priv- ilege in the client certificate, and permit- ting access.Each .xdaaccess file applies to Web pages in its directory and all subdirectories. It contains ACL entries that explicitly allow or deny access on the basis of a privilege. For example, if Man- ager and Officer are privileges, an .xdaaccess file might contain the lines:4.3 PGSThe PGS is implemented as an OCSP re- sponder for X.509 certificates. This respon- der is compliant with RFC25603). The OCSP status information for certificates is received from an LDAP server specifying the certificate database.The PGS is implemented as a Java servlet ex- ecuted by Tomcat. The configuration files for the PGS servlet contain initialization parame- ters for the servlet and set up a secure area used by the servlet.4.4 ProxyThe proxy is an SSL proxy written in Java. It assumes that the server will request a client certificate for secure SSL connections. SSL ver- sions 3.0 and 3.1 are supported in our exper- imental implementation. Since there are no other constrains on the machine on which the proxy runs, it can be run on the end-user’s ma- chine so that there is one proxy per user, or it can be executed as a client-side proxy in which case many users are associate to one proxy.The proxy listens for a client certificate passed from the client to a server. Once de- tected, the proxy forwards the client certificate to the OCSP responder (PGS). The proxy re- ceives the OCSP response and forwards it to an   # Deny everyone except for# Manager and Officerdeny allallow Managerallow Officer  
1610 IPSJ Journal June 2003authorization server in form of an HTTP POST message. The authorization sever can be a static server, or the proxy construct its URL from the SSL server’s IP address, a default port and a directory path defined in the proxy con- figuration file. The proxy assumes that the OCSP response is compliant with RFC2560 3).This proxy can define whether the proxy is contacting the PGS synchronously or asyn- chronously. If the proxy works in a synchronous fashion, it is guaranteed that the authorization server gets the ticket before the SSL handshake between server and client is completed, whereas in the asynchronous mode the handshake may complete without the ticket being arrived at the authorization server. In the latter case, an ac- cess request may be denied, in spite of the fact that the client certificate is valid and has priv- ileges that would allow access.5. DiscussionThe proposed scheme is reminiscent of Ker- beros7) because the PGS performs a function similar to the Ticket Generating Server (TGS) in Kerberos, to create tickets for use with an ap- plication server. The original Kerberos had an Authentication Server to which the user would log in with a password, but currently there are extensions to Kerberos to permit the use of pub- lic key certificate for user identification. Our approach has a very different notion of the pur- pose and structure of a ticket, however, due to its use of public keys and access control in deal- ings with the application servers.The PKDA (Public Key Distributed Authen- tication) approach is another outgrowth of Ker- beros that uses public key certificates8). Its objective is to distribute PGS functions to “PKDA-enabled” servers, and the tickets it generates are essentially Kerberos tickets, con- taining a symmetric session key to be used with a specific server. A ticket in our proposal is dif- ferent because it is a status response associated with a standard X.509 certificate, which con- veys a public key that can be used with avail- able protocols like SSL or TLS to set up au- thentication or data encryption as desired, and it establishes group membership in a way that is not confined to a specific server.If certificates have short validity periods, we may not need the revocation information so much. Because a client certificate was issued within few minutes ago and will expire within short minutes, servers do not need to vali-date the received certificate 9),10) . However, as described in Ref. 9), this short-lived-certificate framework is not appropriate for Internet ap- plications, where there is little control over both clients and servers. In case of short- lived-certificate, both servers and clients need to handle the certificate smartly. For example, the servers need to distinguish the short-lived- certificate and long-lived-certificate. When the servers receive the short-lived-certificate, they should not check the revocation status of it. Therefore, we need to modify the servers to dis- tinguish the short-lived-certificate. The clients also need modification to handle the short- lived-certificate. Today, most Web browsers assume that certificates are long-lived. For example, these browsers do not automatically removed expired certificates and their associ- ated key pairs. Because the Web browsers must obtain a new certificate whenever starting or expiring a previous certificate under short- lived-certificate framework, management of cer- tificates annoys the users of browsers without modification. Since our approach does not need to update the certificate frequently, it is said that this approach is appropriate for general Web browsers.In Section 2.3, we avoid to use of the CRL. Though one of the reason is lack of scala- bility, delta-CRL may resolve this problem 2) . Because difference between the previous CRL and current CRL is sent under the delta-CRL framework, communication overhead for send- ing the CRL may decrease with this mechanism. However the size of revocation information is unpredictable under the delta-CRL mechanism. Moreover, several problems described in Sec- tion 2.3 are not resolved by using the delta- CRL. Since the server sends minimum revoca- tion information on appropriate timing in our approach, the proposed scheme is superior to the delta-CRL under multiple domain environ- ment.6. ConclusionsWe have proposed a PKI mechanism to sup- port access control of a client in one domain to a server in another. When the server and client belong to different PKI domains, the server re- quires retrieving a CRL or accessing to an on- line verification server, such as an OCSP re- sponder, to check a revocation status of the client certificate in normal PKI system. How- ever, from the viewpoint on security, it is not
Vol. 44 No. 6 Notification of Certificate Revocation Status between Different Domains 1611desirable for the client domain to provide an access point outside of an Internet firewall and to distribute unnecessary information. There- fore we have proposed the mechanism to attach a ticket that includes the revoked status of cer- tificate with the sending client certificate. With this mechanism, only the minimum status infor- mation is sent, it is sent unforgeably, and only when access is requested. The external access point to distribute status information to other domains is not required.In order to implement this architecture eas- ily into the WWW environment, we designed a system architecture that does not require mod- ification to Web browsers. It uses a Web proxy that observes an SSL connection passively, a PGS module to support ticket generation in conjunction with a client CA, and an authoriza- tion module in the Web server to check access using the certificate and ticket.Access control and authorization at the server are based on the contents of the client certifi- cate, using some form of ACL. While access could be controlled on the basis of the user or subject name, the client CA can also cre- ate client certificates containing a more general privilege field. Access control by privilege is more efficient when the server has many indi- vidual clients, and is willing to trust the client CA to assign server privileges to clients in its domain. This approach can be supported with- out change to the architecture as described.References1) ITU-T Recommendation X.509: Information Technology —Open Systems Interconnection— The Directory: Public-Key and Attribute Cer- tificate Frameworks (2000).2) Housley, R., Ford, W., Polk, W. and Solo, D.: Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure — Certificate and CRL Profile, RFC 2459 (1999).3) Myers,M.,Ankney,R.,Malpani,A.,Galperin, S. and Adams, C.: X.509 Internet Public Key Infrastructure — Online Certificate Sta- tus Protocol — OCSP, RFC 2560 (1999).4) Adams, C. and Farrell, S.: Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure — Certificate Man- agement Protocols, RFC 2510 (1999).5) Freier, A., Karlton, P. and Kocher, P.: The SSL Protocol: Version 3.0, Netscape Commu- nications Corp. (1999).6) Dierks, T. and Allen, C.: The TLS Protocol – Version 1.0, RFC 2246 (1999).7) Kohl, J. and Neuman, C.: The Kerberos Net- work Authentication Service (V5), RFC 1510(1993).8) Sirbu, M. and Chuang, J.: Distributed Au-thentication in Kerberos Using Public Key Cryptography, Internet Society 1997 Sympo- sium on Network and Distributed System Se- curity (1997).9) Hsu,Y.andSeymour,S.:AnIntranetSecurity Framework Based on Short-Lived Certificates, IEEE Internet Computing, Vol.2, No.2, pp.73– 79 (1998).10) Rivest, R.: Can We Eliminate Certificate Re- vocations Lists?, Financial Cryptography’98, LNCS 1465, pp.178–183 (1998).(Received September 5, 2002) (Accepted March 4, 2003)Editer’s RecommendationThe authors propose a unique method for the very important topic of the distribution of cer- tificate revocation information in PKI.(Chairman of SIGCSEC Eiji Okamoto)Yutaka Miyake received the B.E. and M.E. degrees of Elec- trical Engineering from Keio University, Japan, in 1988 and 1990, respectively. He joined KDD (now KDDI) in 1990, and has been engaged in the researchon high speed communication protocol, secure communicating and privacy protection system for network applications. During a year of 2000 to 2001, he was a visiting researcher at SRI In- ternational and University of California, Berke- ley. He is currently a senior research engineer of Network Security Lab. in KDDI R&D Labora- tories Inc. He received IPSJ Convention Award in 1995. He is a member of IEICE. 
1612IPSJ JournalJune 2003Jonathan K. Millen is a Se- nior Computer Scientist in the Computer Science Laboratory, SRI International, working in the area of dependable systems and cryptographic protocol ver- ification. From 1969 to 1997 heworked at The MITRE Corporation. He is co- Editor-in-Chief of the Journal of Computer Se- curity, an associate editor of the ACM Trans- actions on Information and System Security, and the founder of the annual IEEE Computer Security Foundations Workshop. He holds a Ph.D. in Mathematics from Rensselaer Poly- technic Institute, an M.S. from Stanford, and an A.B. from Harvard.Grit Denker is a Computer Scientist in the Computer Sci- ence Laboratory at SRI Interna- tional in California. From 1995 to 1996 she worked as an as- sistant professor at the Techni- cal University of Braunschweigin Germany. Her main areas of interest are formal specification and verification of cryp- tographic security protocols, security for the Semantic Web, and logic-based approaches for distributed system analysis. She holds a Ph.D. in Computer Science and an M.S. in Mathe- matics from the Technical University of Braun- schweig.Toshiaki Tanaka received the B.E. and M.E. degrees of Communication Engineering from Osaka University, Japan, in 1984 and 1986 respectively. He joined KDD (now KDDI) and has been engaged in the re-search on network security, cryptographic pro- tocol, mobile security, digital rights manage- ment, and intrusion detection techniques. He is currently a senior manager of Network Secu- rity Lab. in KDDI R&D Laboratories Inc. He is a member of IEICE.Ko ji Nakao received the B.E. degree of Mathematics from Waseda University, Japan, in 1979. He joined KDD (now KDDI) and has been engaged in the research on multime- dia communications, communi-cation protocol, secure communicating system and information security technology for the telecommunications network. He received IPSJ Research Award in 1992. He is a member of IEICE. He has been a part-time instructor in Waseda University and The University of Electro-Communications since 2002.     