Vol. 44 No. 8 IPSJ Journal Aug. 2003Regular PaperAn Adaptive Scheduler to Improve QoS in Input-Buffered SwitchesChun-Xiang Chen† and Masaharu Komatsu††One difficult problem in the current Internet is how to guarantee the Quality of Service (QoS) for each connection. This paper proposes an adaptive scheduler for input-buffered switches to improve QoS guarantees for various traffic classes. The algorithm introduced in the scheduler is based on the required bandwidth of each connection. Our scheduler uni- formly deals with various traffic classes without any strict priority discipline. Thus, it can effectively use the residual resources of the switch for any traffic pattern without facing re- source starvation. From simulation results, it is clarified that the proposed scheduler has bet- ter performance, in terms of throughput, packet delay and deviation, than some well-known schedulers.1. IntroductionThe current Internet has had great success due to the simplicity and the connectivity of the Internet Protocol (IP). The philosophy of IP is to keep the network as simple as possi- ble and leave the complicated processing to end hosts. IP only supports the best-effort service. However, we face a difficult problem when we transmit various types of data including real- time streaming such as movies and audio via the current Internet. The problem is how to guarantee the Quality-of-Service (QoS) for each connection. To provide the QoS guarantees through the best-effort network, two methods can be considered. One is to increase the trans- fer speed of physical circuits and the exchange speed of switches. However, this way is not drastic due to the connection-less nature of the IP, and the packet flow of a connection would be broken by other connections if there were any. The other is by designing switches which provide QoS support.So far, most of the switches with QoS sup- port employ output buffer structure because the departure time of a packet stored in the output buffer can be easily controlled by a sim- ple algorithm to provide QoS guarantee 1),2) . However, in an extreme case, the fabric of an N × N switch must run N times faster than the line speed (called speedup in some litera- ture) 1),3),4) . This is very difficult and some- times impossible when the line speed is very high (up to Tbit/s range) and when the num-† Information Processing Center, Hiroshima Prefec- tural University†† Department of Information and Computer Engi- neering, Okayama University of Scienceber of input-(output-) ports of the switch is very large.On the other hand, the input-buffered (IB) switch only needs to operate as fast as the line speed5)∼7). Therefore, the input buffer is very suitable for switches with a large number of ports and with extremely high line speed. However, the IB switch requires Virtual Out- put Queueing (VOQ) and a scheduler to avoid contentions among the packets which share the same input port and/or the packets which de- part for the same output port. The scheduler selects the packets which would be transmitted in the next time slot. Thus, the algorithm used in the scheduler is especially important since it is directly related to QoS. Considering the advantages and disadvantages of the switches stated above, we employ the IB switch in this paper.To provide QoS guarantee, one of the tradi- tional methods is to give strict priorities to dif- ferent connections (high priority is given to real- time connection) 8)∼10) or reserve a strict band- width for each connection (such as Resource Reservation Protocol (RSVP)). However, these schemes do not provide flexibility and fairness of service. The other methods are to design a smart scheduler to find a suitable matching be- tween the input and the output ports. There are several scheduling programs designed to achieve high performance, such as first-in/first- out (FIFO) with VOQ support, longest queue first (LQF) 5),11) , credit based scheme7) and oldest cell first (OCF) 6) etc. The common mat- ter in these schedulers is to take an appropri- ate parameter as the priority weight when the scheduler selects the next packets. For exam- ple, FIFO (LQF) takes the arrival time (queue 2200
Vol. 44 No. 8 An Adaptive Scheduler to Improve QoS in Input-Buffered Switches 2201       VOQ(0,0) VOQ(0,1)......   VOQ(0,N-1)  q qqJ     q      VOQ(1,0) VOQ(1,1)......   VOQ(1,N-1)  q    qJ  non-blocking switch fabric   q  q    length) of the packet as the priority weight. The credit-based bandwidth reservation scheme7) takes the bandwidth assigned by an admission controller (AC) as the credit. The credit in- creases in proportion to the assigned bandwidth capacity in time slots and is consumed by the incoming packets. However, when the credit is exhausted, packets waiting in the queue are un- able to be transmitted even if there is a surplus of bandwidth.On the communications via Internet, QoS can be quantitatively described with some indexes, such as transmission delay, transmission error, packet loss, deviation of delay, jitter of delay etc. If these indexes are kept within the ex- pectations, the QoS can be considered as being satisfied. In this paper, we use the packet de- lay and its deviation to evaluate the quality of service.In this paper, we focus on the IB switch in which VOQs are employed to overcome head-of- line (HOL) blocking12). The aim of this paper is to design an effective scheduler to select pack- ets to be transmitted in the next time slot. To achieve this, we propose a scheduling algorithm (called MEF: Most Expected packet First) with the aim of improving QoS. The main feature of MEF is that it fairly and flexibly deals with all traffic based on the assigned bandwidth. How- ever, differing from RSVP, MEF only refers to the bandwidth of the connection and does not make a strict bandwidth allocation. The con- tribution of this paper is as follows. First, the MEF algorithm has greater adaptability to deal with multi-traffic classes without using strict priority. Thus, MEF can easily accept new con- nections. Second, MEF has very high flexibility to make effective use of the network resources when total traffic is not at full capacity even if the traffic is unbalanced. Third, MEF does not have the starvation phenomenon 13) even for un- balanced traffic or overload traffic because MEF deals with packets based on the bandwidth of each connection in whole time slots.The rest of this paper is organized as fol- lows. Section 2 gives a simple model of the IB switch and the definition of symbols used in this paper. The proposed scheduling algorithm is given in Section 3. Section 4 gives the simula- tion method including the traffic patterns dealt with in Section 5. The simulation results com- pared with the other schedulers are shown in Section 5, and finally the concluding remarks are stated in Section 6.Input J Output --    Port 0Port 0      Input J --Port 1...... ......VOQ(M-1,0) JInput VOQ(M-1,1) J OutputOutput Port 1            -- Port M-1 ......   Port N-1      2.VOQ(M-1,N-1)  Fig. 1 M × N ATM switch with VOQ.Switching ModelA simple M × N IB switch with VOQs is shown in Fig. 1. We assume that the length of packet is fixed☆, and the time axis is di- vided into fixed-length units (called time slots) in which at most one packet arrives at each input-port and/or is transmitted to its des- tined output-port. The switch includes a non- blocking fabric which is able to concurrently send min(N,M) packets to the corresponding output ports. The packet destined to output port j arrives at input port i, is temporarily stored in the corresponding FIFO VOQ(i, j) and waits to be transmitted, where 0 ≤ i ≤ M−1and0≤j≤N−1.The operation of FIFO VOQ is as follows. If a nonempty VOQ is selected by the scheduler, the packet at the head of the VOQ can be transmit- ted, and would be removed immediately after the end of its transmission. Obviously, at most one nonempty VOQ in an input port would be selected to transmit its head packet.Without loss of generality, we assume that the transmission capacity (bandwidth) of the switch is initialized as 1. The switch has no speedup. We give some terms and assumptions as follows:☆ It is likely that the packet size would vary within different switches (protocols). However, the packet scheduler is considered to be implemented at the data link layer, and the segmentation and assem- bly are performed at the upper layer. Hence, it is suitable to assume that the packet size is uniform here. 
2202 IPSJ Journal Aug. 2003V Cij : Virtual connection in which a packet arrives at input port i and is destined to output port j. Actually, it is likely that several connections have the same input- output pair; in this case, each connection needs its own QoS guarantee. For simplic- ity, here, we assume that each connection has a distinct input-output pair.aij(n) aij(n + 1) aij(n + 2) aij(n + 3) ????-                          6  T i j - 6 eij(n) eij(n + 1)66t  bijL(i, j) : Capacity of V OQ(i, j).: Bandwidth of V Cij . Thus Tij = 1/bij is the average interarrival time of packets with the same V Cij .Input Ports Output PortsInput Ports0 s  0 @I-1Output PortsInput PortsOutput Portseij(n + 2)Fig. 2 Expected arrival times and real arrival times.0 s 0 - s 0 H 1 * @-1 H  1  H 7s 0 1 s @ -2 s1s 0 1 s@-2-s1eij(n + 3)  1  s-@2  Hj-s1 H0  *0 s @-11    @H  @   The traffic load of each V Cij is bij . Thus the condition that the switch is stable, is as follows:1  @ H@2    s @1    0 @RjH- s 2 2 s @ s 2 2 s @R s 2-H10 * HY H    H    N−1j=0 bij<1, for ∀i1HH 3 s @RjH-s3 3sHs3 3sHjs3H@-1 H 2  H -1  M −1 (1) i=0 bij < 1, for ∀j.Of course, if the above expression is not satis- fied, the switch is unstable or overloaded.3. Scheduling AlgorithmIn this section, we describe the proposed scheduling algorithm (called MEF). Similar to the other weighted-fair schedulers, we carefully choose the priority weight to improve QoS guar- antee. In a connection-oriented network such as ATM (Asynchronous Transfer Mode) network, the rate of packet generation would be declared and allocated by AC according to the remain- ing resource of the network. Surely, the band- width allowed (assigned) by AC is not always the same as the packet rate requested by the connection. Thus the assigned bandwidth is able to be considered as the average arrival rate from the connection. Let eij (n) be the expected arrival time of the n-th packet from connection(Fig. 2). Obviously, the expected arrival time of the next packet, eij (n + 1), satisfieseij(n + 1)=eij(n) + Tij, Tij =1/bij. (2) Unfortunately, the real arrival time is not al- ways the same as the expected time. It would be influenced by other connections. Let aij(n) be the real arrival time of the n-th packet from V Cij . Furthermore, let wij (n) be the interval from the current time to the expected arrival time of the packet. We havewij(n) = eij(n) − tnow, (3) where tnow is the current time. wij means the urgency of the transmission of the n-th packet. Therefore, wij(n) can be considered as a very fair priority weight to the n-th packet in its transmission. The packet with smaller wij (n) is assigned higher priority. Now the MEF algo-0A: Request B: Grant C: AcceptFig. 3 An example of the first iteration for a 4 × 4 switch.rithm can be given as follows:(1) Calculate wij of each HOL packet inVOQs if it exists.(2) Request: Each unmatched☆ input port,in which there is at least one packet in its VOQ, sends the requests (including the priority weight wij) to the corresponding output ports.(3) Grant: If an unmatched output port j re-ceives any requests, it selects input portk, which satisfies wkj = min(wij), and igrants the request to input port k.(4) Accept: If input port k receives anygrants, it accepts the output port hamong these outputs from which grantshave been received, where h satisfieswkh = min(wkj ), and informs output jport h of this acceptance. Thus an input-output pair (k, h) is established.(5) Repeat above steps 2, 3 and 4 until all of the possible pairs are established amonginput-output ports.An example of the first iteration of MEF isshown in Fig. 3 for a 4×4 switch. After the first iteration, pairs (0, 2), (1, 1) and (2, 3) are estab- lished. Then the algorithm enters the second iteration. Input port 3 sends its request to out- put ports 0, 1, 2 and 3 (step 2), and input port 3 receives only a grant from output port 0 (step☆ The goal of the scheduler is to find the input-output pairs. If an input port is paired with an output port by the scheduler, we say that this input/output port is matched; inversely, this input/output is un- matched.V Cij 
Vol. 44 No. 8 An Adaptive Scheduler to Improve QoS in Input-Buffered Switches 22033). Thus, the pair (3, 0) is established (step 4). After the second iteration, all of the possible pairs have been established. The MEF algo- rithm finds all the possible pairs, on average, in O(log H) iterations 13), where H = min(M, N).4. Simulation MethodTo evaluate the performance of our scheduler with simulation, we consider an M × N switch, where M is the number of input ports and N the number of output ports. We also assume three kinds of arrival traffic patterns as follows:(1) Constant interval traffic — The interar-rival time of packets is precisely equal toa constant. It means that there is ex-actly one arrival at the end of each in-terval time. Let Tij be the constant in- γ= terarrival of the packets from connectionV Cij . Then, the average load is given byαij=1/Tij,wherei∈[0,M−1], j ∈ [0, N − 1].(2) Geometric traffic — The interarrival time of the packets is distributed according toa geometric distribution. Let fij (n) be the probability that the interarrival of the packets from V Cij is n time slots. fij(n) is given byfij(n)=gij(1−gij)n−1, n=1,2,3,...(4) where gij is the arrival rate of the packet from V Cij in a time slot. Thus, the aver- age interval time is 1/gij and the average load (βij) is βij = gij.(3) Burst traffic — The packet arrives ac- cording to a two-state Markov chain. One state is called On in which one packet arrives in each slot time. The other is called Off in which there are no arrivals (Fig. 4).If we assume that the transition probability of the burst connection V Cij from state On to On is pij and the transition probability from state Off to Off is qij, then the average length of state On (Bij ) and the average length of state Off (Sij) are shown asBij= 1, Sij= 1. (5) 1−pij 1−qijTherefore, let γij be the average load of the burst connection V Cij . γij is given asγij = Bij , (6) Bij + Sijand let ρi be the traffic load of input port i, which is obtained byN−1   ρi =(αij +βij +γij). (7)j=0Now, let α, β and γ be the total arrival rate of the three traffic classes respectively. They are given as α=   αij, for all constant interval traffic,βij, for all geometric traffic,β=Also let α0, β0 and γ0 be the ratios of the threeγij, for all burst traffic. (8)traffic classes respectively. α0= α , α+β+γ ββ0 = α + β + γ , γ γ0 = α + β + γ . (9)        Now, considering the MEF scheduling algo- rithm described in Section 3, the main point in the algorithm is to consider the traffic load of a connection in a long time period (i.e., the average load). Thus the bandwidth of each con- nection is distributed as its average load by the AC.5. Simulation ResultsIn this section, we investigate the charac- teristics of the presented scheduler (MEF) us- ing simulation. Also, the results obtained un- der MEF, are compared with well-known algo- rithms FIFO, LQF 11) and Credit card 7) . The FIFO algorithm takes the arrival time, the LQF algorithm takes the queue length in each VOQ and the Credit card algorithm takes the credit, as the priority weight, respectively. For the traffic classes, we consider the three types of communications described in the previous sec- tion. The burst traffic, such as compressed movies and audio communications, can be con- sidered as real-time traffic; the constant in- terval traffic, such as the FTP, uncompressed video and audio communications, can be con- sidered as real-time constant bit rate traffic; and the geometric traffic can be considered as general data transmission (best-effort commu-pij 1−pij qij                                                                                                                 - On   ROff         State transition of the burst traffic V Cij .      I 1−qij                                                      Fig. 4
2204 IPSJ JournalAug. 2003Table 1 Throughput comparison : 32 × 32 switch.(α0 = 0.375, β0 = 0.422, γ0 = 0.203, Bij = 5)ρi FIFO 0.60 0.9943 0.75 0.9947 0.90 0.9946nications). Thus, it is suitable to assume that the burst traffic and constant interval traffic re- quire the QoS guarantee and the geometric traf- fic does not require the QoS guarantee. Fur- thermore, we assume that each VOQ has infi- nite capacity.In the simulation, the type and the traffic load of each V C are set as follows. The simula- tor randomly generates a V Cij (∀i, ∀j) and its traffic load (bij), where bij must satisfy expres- sion (1), or bij is set to be zero (this connection is refused because the bandwidth requested ex- ceeds the remaining resources. So this process can be considered as a simple emulator of the AC). Here, we let the upper bound of the band- width of each V C be 0.1☆ . The simulation runs until it converges (more than 10,000,000 time slots).Table 1 gives the comparison of throughput in different schedulers for a 32×32 switch. The throughput is defined as the ratio of the num- ber of successfully transmitted packets to the total number of packets arrived in a long time interval. Table 1 shows that all of these sched- ulers achieve about 100% (≥ 99%) throughput by introducing VOQ. We also investigated the throughput in various M , N and other parame- ters. As a result, it was shown that the through- put is about 100% in all cases. Here we omit those comparison tables.Generally, different schedulers provide differ- ent QoS for different traffic classes. It is likely that providing better QoS for a traffic class will sacrifice the QoS of another traffic class when the switch runs at high traffic load 14) . There- fore, it is very important to provide the required QoS for the connections which really need QoS guarantees. In the following, we compare the packet delay, queue length and standard devia- tion of the packet delay in different schedulers.The packet delay (d) is defined as the interval time slots from the arrival time of a packet to the time slot in which it is successfully trans-☆ If the port speed of the switch is faster than 1 Gbps, 0.1 (corresponding to 100 Mbps) is sufficient to sat- isfy the practical applications.100 80 60 40 20 00.4 0.50.6 0.7 0.8 Traffic Load0.9 1            MEF B=5LQF B=5 Credit B=5 FIFO B=5 MEF B=8 LQF B=8 Credit B=8 FIFO B=8  MEF  Credit LQF 0.9943 0.9947 0.9944    0.9917 0.9923 0.9916     0.9943 0.9947 0.9945                             Fig. 5Average packet delay of constant interarrival- time traffic(32 × 32 switch, α0 = 0.375, β0 = 0.422, γ0 = 0.203). 100           Fig. 6Average packet delay of geometric traffic80 60 40 2000.4 0.50.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 Traffic LoadMEF B=5 LQF B=5 FIFO B=5 Credit B=5 MEF B=8 LQF B=8 Credit B=8 FIFO B=8                       (32 × 32 switch, α0 = 0.375, β0 = 0.422, γ0 = 0.203). 100            Fig. 7Average packet delay of burst traffic80 60 40 2000.4 0.50.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 Traffic LoadMEF B=5LQF B=5 Credit B=5 FIFO B=5 MEF B=8 LQF B=8 Credit B=8 FIFO B=8                       (32 × 32 switch, α0 = 0.375, β0 = 0.422, γ0 = 0.203).mitted to the output port. Figures 5, 6 and 7 give the average delays of the constant in- terval, geometric and burst traffic classes, re- spectively, where B is the average burst length of the burst traffic class. From these figures, it is clear that (1) the average delays of con- stant interval traffic and the burst traffic, under MEF, are relatively smaller and increase slowly with the increase of the traffic load (ρi) even if the traffic load is high (up to 0.95); whereas the average delay of geometric traffic increases sharply when ρi > 0.7. This is true because, as the traffic load is very high, MEF adaptively serves the burst traffic and the constant traf- Packet Delay Packet Delay Packet Delay
Vol. 44 No. 8 An Adaptive Scheduler to Improve QoS in Input-Buffered Switches 2205fic with high priority. (2) The average delay under the Credit card scheme is the worst, es- pecially for the geometric traffic and the burst traffic because the packet of a connection is un- able to get the service if the credit is exhausted even though surplus resources exist. The result agrees with that in Ref.7). (3) The average delays for all the traffic types, under FIFO, in- crease in the same way when the traffic load increases. (4) The average delay, under LQF, has some resemblance to that of FIFO. (5) The burst length strongly influences the packet de- lay, the bigger the burst length, the longer the packet delay.To evaluate the performance of QoS providedby each scheduler, only the packet delay is in-sufficient. The jitter of the packet delay mustbe investigated. Here the jitter of the packet de-lay is evaluated by the standard deviation (σ).σ is defined as   100 80 60 40 20 00.4 0.50.6 0.7 0.8 Traffic Load0.9 1                                             NP (di − average packet delay)2σ=i=1 ,0NPwhere, NP is the total number of the packetswhich belong to that traffic class and di is the delay of each packet.Figures 8–10 give the standard deviation of each traffic class. Figures 8 and 10 show that the standard deviations of the constant traffic or the burst traffic, under MEF, increase grad- ually as the traffic load increases. Comparing with other schedulers, MEF gives the small- est standard deviation. However, the standard deviation of the geometric traffic (Fig.9) in- creases sharply, especially at ρi > 0.7. Thus, it is evident that MEF improves the QoS of the constant interval traffic and the burst traf- fic at the cost of the geometric traffic’s QoS when traffic load is relatively high. The stan- dard deviation of each class in the FIFO scheme has a similar trend. In other words, the FIFO scheme serves all classes without difference even if some classes need the QoS guarantees. The credit card scheme, as before, gives the worst performance in terms of σ. Also, the influence of the burst length of the burst traffic class is il- lustrated in the same figures. It is clear that the longer the burst length, the higher the standard deviation.Other results with different parameters are shown in Figs. 11, 12 and 13 (where B = 5). The performance changes with the parameters. However, it is clear that the performance (in terms of throughput and deviation) of the MEF0.4 0.50.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 Traffic LoadFig. 8Standard deviation of constant interval trafficMEF B=5 LQF B=5 FIFO B=5 Credit B=5 MEF B=8 LQF B=8 FIFO B=8 Credit B=8         (32 × 32 switch, α0 = 0.375, β0 = 0.422, γ0 = 0.203). 10080 60 40 20MEF B=5LQF B=5 Credit B=5 FIFO B=5 MEF B=8 LQF B=8 Credit B=8 FIFO B=8                    Fig. 9 Standard deviation of geometric traffic (32 × 32 switch, α0 = 0.375, β0 = 0.422, γ0 = 0.203).100 80 60 40 2000.4 0.50.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 Traffic Load            Fig. 10Standard deviation of burst trafficMEF B=5 LQF B=5 FIFO B=5 Credit B=5 MEF B=8 LQF B=8 Credit B=8 FIFO B=8                                     (32 × 32 switch, α0 = 0.375, β0 = 0.422, γ0 = 0.203).scheduler is better than the other schedulers. We also investigated the average packet delay, and the standard deviation in various B, M, N , α0 , β0 and γ0 for each traffic class. The simulation results in all cases show that MEF gives a better performance in terms of packet delay and σ than the other schedulers for the constant interarrival time traffic and the burst traffic. We omit these figures because of space limitations.In our simulation, we assumed that each VOQ has infinite capacity. We also investigated the queue length of each VOQ. The maximal queue length is shown in Fig. 14. We can see from Fig. 14 that the necessary buffer size underStandard deviation Standard deviation Standard deviation
2206IPSJ Journal Aug. 2003               Fig. 11Average packet delay of constant interarrival- time traffic           Fig. 12Average packet delay of constant interarrival- time traffic100 80 60 40 20 00.4 0.50.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 Traffic Loadthe MEF scheduler is relatively shorter.6. Concluding RemarksIt is a difficult problem to provide QoS guar- antees in the current Internet. However, once the Internet has become an integrated infras- tructure of communications, especially as a commercial communication infrastructure, it becomes essential that the Internet can guar- antee the QoS for each connection.In this paper, trying to improve the QoS, we presented a scheduling algorithm, called MEF, based on the bandwidth of each connection. MEF can not be implemented directly in IP networks due to the connection-less nature of the Internet protocol. However, MEF could be implemented in the core switch of networks in which traffic engineering is becoming more prevalent to provide connection-oriented packet switching for certain input-output connections (e.g., ATM networks, MPLS (Multi-Protocol Label Switching) networks) 15). In such net- works, the bandwidth of each connection is de- clared at the establishment of the connection. MEF skillfully uses the bandwidth and adap- tively provides packet scheduling for the switch.To show the advantage of MEF, we compared its performance with some well-known sched- ulers. From the simulation results, it was shown that LQF and FIFO schedulers provide service to each traffic class without any distinction. On the other hand, MEF outperforms the FIFO or LQF schedulers with respect to QoS measured in terms of average packet delay and standard deviation. Furthermore, in contrast to RSVP, MEF does not require the actual bandwidth al- location; it only refers to the bandwidth of the connection. Thus the MEF scheme does not use strict priority in different traffic classes. This makes the MEF scheme simpler and more flex- ible to be implemented in edge routers. Also, MEF has no starvation phenomenon13) which occurs in some other schemes (such as LQF) because the priority of the packet waiting in VOQ adaptively becomes higher as the time slot passes.Acknowledgments The authors would like to thank the anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments.References1) Liebeherr, J. and Wrege, D.E.: Priority Queue Schedulers with Approximate Sorting in Output-Buffered Switches, IEEE JournalMEF B=5 FIFO B=5 MEF B=8 FIFO B=8MEF LQF FIFO Credit                  (48 × 48 switch, α0 = 0.507, β0 = 0.312, γ0 = 0.181). 10080 60 40 2000.4 0.50.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 Traffic LoadMEF LQF FIFO Credit                   (48 × 48 switch, α0 = 0.181, β0 = 0.312, γ0 = 0.507). 100           Fig. 13Standard deviation of burst traffic80 60 40 2000.4 0.50.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 Traffic LoadMEF LQF FIFO                               (48 × 48 switch, α0 = 0.277, β0 = 0.322, γ0 = 0.401). 100                  80 60 40 200 0.20.30.40.5 0.6 0.7 Traffic Load0.8 0.9 1                                        Fig. 14Maximal queue Length(32 × 32 switch, α0 = 0.375, β0 = 0.422, γ0 = 0.203).Maximal queue Length Standard Deviation Packet Delay Packet Delay
Vol. 44 No. 8 An Adaptive Scheduler to Improve QoS in Input-Buffered Switches 2207on Selected Areas in Commun., Vol.17, No.6,pp.1127–1144 (1999).2) Schoenen, R.: An Architecture SupportingQuality of Service in Virtual-Output-Queued Switches, IEICE Trans. Commun., Vol.E83-B, No.2, pp.171–181 (2000).3) Chuang, S.-T., Goel, A., McKeown, N. and Prabhakar, B.: Matching Output Queue- ing with a Combined Input/Output-Queued Switch, IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Commun., Vol.17, No.6, pp.1030–1039 (1999).4) Krishna, P., Patel, N.S., Charny, A. and Simcoe, R.J.: On the Speedup Required for Work-Conserving Crossbar Switches, IEEE Journal on SAC, Vol.17, No.6, pp.1057–1066 (1999).5) Mekkittikul, A. and McKeown, N.: A Prac- tical Scheduling Algorithm to Achieve 100% Throughput in Input-Queued Switches, IEEE INFOCOM’98, Vol.2, pp.792–799 (Apr. 1998).6) Nabeshima, M. and Yamanaka, N.: The i-QOCF: Scheduling Algorithm for Input- Queued ATM Switches, IEICE Trans. Com- mun., Vol.E83-B, No.2 pp.182–189 (2000).7) Kam, A.C. and Siu, K.-Y.: Linear-Complexity Algorithms for QoS Support in Input-Queued Switches with No Speedup, IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Commun., Vol.17, No.6, pp.1042–1056 (1999).8) Chen, W.-T., Lee, R.-R. and Lin, H.-J.: A Novel Cell Scheduler with QoS Guarantee for Services in ATM Networks, IEICE Trans.Com- mun., Vol.E82-B, No.2, pp.447–454 (1999).9) Oki, E., Yamanaka, N. and Nabeshima, M.: Performance of Scalable-Distributed-Arbi- tration ATM Switch Supporting Multiple QoS Classes, IEICE Trans. Commun., Vol.E83-B, No.2, pp.204–213 (2000).10) Marsan, M.A., Bianco, A., Leonardi, E. and Milia, L.: RPA: A Flexible Scheduling Al- gorithm for Input Buffered Switches, IEEE Trans. Commun., Vol.47, No.12, pp.1921–1933 (1999).11) McKeown, N., Mekkittikul, A., Anantharam, V. and Walrand, J.: Achieving 100% Through- put in an Input-Queued Switch, IEEE Trans. Commun., Vol.47, No.8, pp.1260–1267 (1999).12) Karol, M., Hluchyj, M. and Morgan, S.: Input versus Output Queueing on a space- division switch, IEEE Trans. Commun., Vol.35, pp.1347–1356 (1987).13) McKeown, N.: The iSLIP Scheduling Algo- rithm for Input-Queued Switches, IEEE Trans. on Networking, Vol.7, No.2 (1999).14) Wang, F. and Mohapatra, P.: An Efficient Bandwidth Management Scheme for Real- Time Internet Application, International Sym- posium on Intelligent Multimedia, Video and Speech Processing (2001).15) Hsu, N.-B., Lin, Y.-D., Li, M.-H. and Lee, T.-H.: Service-Sensitive Routing in Diff- Serv/MPLS Networks, IEICE Trans. Com- mun., Vol.E84-B, No.10, pp.2871–2879 (2001).(Received August 12, 2002) (Accepted May 6, 2003)Chun-Xiang Chen received the B.E. degree from Sichuan University, Sichuan, China in 1986, the M.E. and Ph.D. de- grees from Kanazawa University and Osaka University, Japan, in 1991, 1994, respectively. From1994 to 1996, he was an assistant professor in the Department of Computer Engineering at Hiroshima City University, Japan. Since May 1997, he has been an Associate Professor at Hiroshima Prefectural University, Hiroshima, Japan. His current research interests include performance evaluation of communication net- works, high speed switching and QoS on the Internet. He is a member of the IEICE, the IPS of Japan and the IEEE Communications society.Masaharu Komatsu re- ceived B.E., M.E., and Dr. E. degrees in Communication Engi- neering from Osaka University, Osaka, Japan, in 1972, 1975, and 1978, respectively. From 1978 to 1987, he was an As-sistant Professor at Hiroshima University, Hi- roshima, Japan. From 1988 to 1991, he was an Associate Professor at Kanazawa Univer- sity, Kanazawa, Japan. From 1991 to 2001, he was an Associate Professor at Osaka University, Osaka, Japan. Since April 2001, he has been a Professor in the Department of Information and Computer Engineering at Okayama University of Science, Okayama, Japan. His current in- terests include performance evaluation of com- munication systems, ATM switching and error control protocols. He is a member of the IPS of Japan and the IEEE.   