Vol. 44 No. 8 IPSJ Journal Aug. 2003Regular PaperEnhancing Airport Access Control Securitywith Multiple Biometrics Contactless Smart CardMichael W. David† and Kouichi Sakurai††This paper looks at the issues facing biometrics technologies and smart cards. It then discusses ways to overcome these issues. The proposal is to use of multiple biometric features in contactless smart cards (CSC). The paper describes a sample generic airport access control security system. It recommends biometric features like the user’s fingerprint, face or iris to provide authentication of the person presenting the card for access to a facility, or use of an application. The paper also suggests possible use of device features like uniquely identifiable semiconductor chips in combination with biometric features and personal data to enhance security for logical access in the future.1. IntroductionThe events of September 11th 2001 have ac- celerated efforts to improve methods and means of individual identification (ID) for both phys- ical and logical access. Anyone who has been to an airport since September 11th should be aware of the increased scrutiny given to pas- senger identification and baggage checks. Bio- metrics and smart cards have been proposed as tools to support the passenger identifica- tion process. To date the United States has been lagging behind Europe and Asia in the introduction and use of smart card technol- ogy12). However, the U.S. has been catching up, and initiated the Department of Defense (DOD) Common Access Card (CAC). Con- tactless smart cards are being used in tran- sit systems in Washington DC and Chicago. DOD has created a Biometrics Management Of- fice (BMO) to consolidate oversight and man- agement of biometric technology for DOD 28) . Questions linger about the security of smart cards and the reliability of fingerprint readers and facial recognition systems. However, devel- opments in contactless smart cards, biometric products and semiconductor production meth- ods are providing an effective means to use mul- tiple features to support secure identification and verification 21),25). The paper proposes the integration of these technologies for use in mul- tiple biometrics smart cards for identity authen- tication and access control, and suggests an im- mediate application for use in airport security† Cubic Corporation†† Faculty of Information Science and Electrical Engi-neering, Kyushu Universitysystems.2. Smart CardsContact smart cards must be inserted into a card reader. They transfer data between the smart card and the reader/writer (r/w) unit through the use of six metallic connectors or contacts found on the surface of the card. When they make physical contact with the connec- tors to transfer data from the chip, the con- nectors receive an electrical voltage to power the MPU. The contact plate provides an in- put/output path for the transaction of data. However, they must be inserted into the r/w units that have movable parts, and these r/w units require extensive maintenance 26) .The contactless smart card (CSC) has no sur- face contacts. The CSC has an integrated cir- cuit (IC) chip and a radio frequency (RF) an- tenna embedded in it. The card must pass near an antenna to carry out a transaction. Power is transferred by an inductive loop using low- frequency radiation from an electromagnetic field, and an electrical-magnetic transformation occurs through the same antenna that trans- mits and receives data. The CSC gets its power from the RF field. The CSC uses proximity r/w units that have no moving parts, and are not as susceptible to maintenance failure under heat, humidity, dust or vibration. Typically, a CSC can process and transaction in 150-300 mi- croseconds versus the 1.5 seconds for a contact card supporting a similar application 26).3. Biometric TechnologiesBiometrics measures individuals’ unique physical or behavioral characteristics to recog- nize or authenticate their identity. Common 2021
2022IPSJ Journal Comparison of biometrics.Aug. 2003Signature High Changing SignaturesHigh* Medium Medium MediumTable 1  Finger  Hand Retina Iris Face High  High Low Medium Medium Dryness, Dirt, Age (**)    Injury, Age     Glasses   Poor Lighting   Lighting, Age, Hair, Glasses   High  High Very High Very High High *  * * * * Medium  Medium Medium Medium Medium High  Medium High Very High Medium High   Medium   High  High  Medium  Characteristic Ease of Use Error incidenceAccuracy Cost Acceptance Security level Long-term stability        * The large number of factors involved makes a simple cost comparison impractical.Source. “A Practical Guide to Biometric Security Technology”, IT Professional, Jan/Feb 2001 15) * Authors’ Comment: Voice Recognition is deleted from the original table.physical biometrics includes fingerprints; handor palm geometry; and retina, iris or facialcharacteristics. Behavioral characters includesignature and voice. Generally speaking, theless intrusive the biometric, the more readily itis accepted. However, certain users, religiousgroups and civil-liberties groups have rejectedbiometric technologies because of privacy con- cerns 15),27).Organizations should determine the level of security needed based on the application and the surrounding environment. This will in- fluence which biometric(s) are most appropri- ate. That is, different biometrics may be ap- propriate for different applications, depending on perceived user profiles, the need to interface with other systems or databases, physical and environmental conditions and a host of other application-specific parameters. Table 1 pro- vides a comparison of various biometric features against a number of characteristics. The com- ments in row three, error incidence, identify fac- tors that can impact on the ability to properly accept or reject the biometric feature. This ta- ble does not include “artificial” biometrics. Ar- tificial fingerprints will be addressed based on research by T. Matsumoto of Yokohama Na- tional University, and discussed in the section on issues for biometric technologies. We will also consider the impact of other artificial bio- metrics separately.4. Issues for Biometric Technologies and Smart CardsResearchers at Yokohama National Univer- sity (YNU) have been working on artificial fin- gers for the past few years. The most recent results have reported attacks using artificial gummy fingers; namely artificial fingers made of inexpensive and readily available gelatin. Thesegummy fingers were accepted at extremely high rates by particular fingerprint devices with opti- cal or capacitive sensors. The research revealed there are many possible attacks to deceive com- mercial fingerprint readers, even if the tem- plates and communications are protected by se- cure measures. Most noticeably, eleven types of fingerprint systems accepted the gummy fingers in their enrollment procedures and also with the rather higher probability in their verifica- tion procedures16). This should be a special concern for airports and other types of facili- ties that have large numbers or employees, and multiple access points, which may not be under visual observation by a guard or online surveil- lance system.The Facial Recognition Vendors Test (FRVT) 2000 was sponsored by multiple U.S. govern- ment agencies to evaluate facial recognition sys- tems. FRVT 2000 performed a technology eval- uation titled “Recognition Performance Test” and a limited scenario evaluation titled “Prod- uct Usability Test” 6) . The overall conclu- sion for recognition performance tests stated the FRVT 2000 showed that progress has been made in temporal changes, but developing al- gorithms that can handle temporal variations is still a necessary research area. In addition, developing algorithms that can compensate for pose variations, and illumination and distance changes were noted as other areas for future re- search. The FRVT 2002 began in June 2002, but the results have not yet been announced5). Masks may be used to try to deceive a fa- cial recognition system, but this should be de- tectable at a manned entry point somewhere in the system.Iris scanning is less intrusive than retina scan- ning. It utilizes a fairly conventional CCD cam- era element and requires no intimate contact
Vol. 44 No. 8 Access Control Security with Multiple Biometrics Contactless Smart Card 2023between user and reader. As a technology it has attracted the attention of many integrators. It has been demonstrated to work with spectacles in place and with a variety of ethnic groups, and is one of the devices that can work well in the identification as well as authentication mode. The main practical problem facing deployment of iris scanning is getting the picture without being intrusive. Also, a simple photograph of the target’s iris could make attacks, at least in unattended operations 2).Paul Kocher brought the threat posed to smart cards by power analysis to the atten- tion of industry in 1998. He developed a spe- cific signal-processing technique to extract the key bits used in a block cipher from a col- lection of power curves, without the knowing the implementation details of the card soft- ware. This technique has been called differ- ential power analysis (DPA). Various defenses have been fielded, and new attacks have been mounted. This is an area of active research2).A purely mathematical evaluation suggests that if a strong test is combined with a weaker test, the resulting decision environment is av- eraged, and the combined performance will lie somewhere between the two tests conducted in- dividually. This implies that there is a need to study the actual benefits of combining two bio- metrics versus using one strong one. The logical answer though is not all people can be enrolled on one biometrics; therefore an alternative fea- ture or method of verification is necessary9).5. Dealing with the IssuesAlthough the results from Yokohama Na- tional University (YNU) provide ample room for improvement, they do not entirely eliminate fingerprint recognition as a valuable biometric feature for identifying an individual. Proba- bly the most important lessons are the need to have more than one biometric feature, proper, live enrollment procedures and interface with the application system that will confirm the au- thenticity of the individual. That is, supervised and reliable enrollment supported by physical or alternative biometric authentication if nec- essary.Figure 1 demonstrates the flow of how a live fingerprint is presented to the reader for cap- turing. The fingerprint feature data is then ex- tracted by the sensors and related algorithms. The data is recorded on a smart card and/or database, and then compared again for correct-Fig. 1Sample fingerprint enrollment system. Matsumoto, T. “Case Study for User Identifi- cation”, ITU-Workshop on Security, May 2002.                                                                                                                                                                                              ness before the final result is registered and stored for future use. This registration should be done in the presence of a trusted party, and the registrant should have valid identification documents and clearances as appropriate to the situation.The risk of acceptance of a false fingerprint is greatly reduced when supervised systems make some check for liveness, however, supervision does not equal a biometric live and well test by high quality sensors. The enrollment pro- cesses in Fig. 1 emphasizes the need for live en- rollment, which should also be supervised by trusted personnel.As noted in the FRVT 2000 report, facial recognition is an area that needs additional research. However, we believe improvements have been made since FRVT 2000, and antici- pate more reliable algorithms and correspond- ing products will be available. One methodol- ogy could be based on Hausdorff distance based models. Research in 2001 indicated this allows for an efficient approach to achieve fast, accu- rate face detection that is robust to changes in illumination and background 11) .There has also been encouraging research re- ported in early June 2002. One report on a complete scheme for face recognition based on salient feature extraction in challenging con- ditions was performed without any a priori or learned model. These features were used in a matching process that overcomes occlu- sion effects and facial expressions using dy- namic space warping to align each feature in the query image, if possible, with its correspond- ing feature in the template or database 20) . Another report entitled “Understanding Iconic Image-Based Face Biometrics” describes a sys-
2024 IPSJ Journal Aug. 2003tem for personal identity verification and recog- nition based on academic and industrial data sets. The experimental results reportedly show greatly improved performance reaching almost 100% recognition 23) . Facial recognition is also less intrusive than iris scanning, and faster for use in high volume passenger areas like board- ing gates.A DOD Biometrics Fusion Center (BFC) product evaluation has looked at a number of iris scanning products. In general, these have been rated overall as “excellent” in their abil- ity to meet DOD requirements 14) . As far as is known, every human iris is measurably unique, even for identical twins. It is fairly easy to de- tect in a video picture, does not wear out, and is isolated from the external environment by the cornea. The iris pattern contains a large amount of randomness, and appears to have many times the degrees of freedom of a fin- gerprint. A possible solution to the imperson- ation problem is to design terminals that mea- sure hippus, a natural fluctuation in the diam- eter of the pupil, which happens at about 0.5 hertz. Iris codes remain a very strong contender as they can, under the correct circumstances, provide much greater certainty than any other method that the individual in question is the same as the one who was initially registered on the system. They can meet the goal of auto- matic recognition with zero false acceptance 2).In practice, iris scanning is proving quite successful. The Amsterdam Schiphol airport has been using an Automatic Border Passage (ABP) system since October 2001. The secu- rity procedure for this system has two phases. The first is qualification and registration. This process includes a passport review, background check and iris scan that is encrypted and em- bedded on a smart card. The second phase identifies and verifies the registered traveler at the border passage checkpoint. The system reads the smart card and allows valid registered travelers to enter an isolated area. The trav- eler then looks into an iris scan camera so the iris can be matched with the data on the smart card. If the match is successful, the traveler ex- its, if it fails, the traveler is directed to the front of the standard queue for passport check10).The Canadian Customs and Revenue Agency will also begin to use iris scanners to speed air travelers through the country’s busiest airports. Those who want the service will submit to a background security check, including a criminalrecord search. The International Air Transport Association (IATA) has indicated that scanning eyes is its preferred biometric choice. One im- portant factor for the IATA is that using the eye as an individual’s unique identifier appears to be the most socially neutral. For example, a Muslim woman could be identified without touching her or asking her to drop her veil 1),27) .The State Department has tried hand recog- nition and retinal scanning without success, but the technology is moving toward iris scanning and face recognition 4) .As for smart cards attacks, for every attack, there is usually a suitable defense. It is the age-old paradigm of the defense versus the of- fense. For example, in May 2002, Ross Ander- son of Cambridge University presented a pa- per at the 2002 Institute of Electrical and Elec- tronics Engineers (IEEE) Symposium on Secu- rity and Privacy entitled Optical Fault Induc- tion Attacks (OFIP). At the same conference, Simon Moore, also of Cambridge, presented a microchip design that could protect against the attack. Moore says: “No single point of fail- ure will result in information being leaked”13). Anderson’s own paper also offers a solution to the OFIP by using self-timed dual-rail circuit design techniques. This technology may also make power analysis attacks more difficult 3).In a different vein, Mitsubishi Electric Cor- poration has developed a semiconductor fabri- cation step that will permit every computer, smart card and semiconductor chip to have its own Artificial Fingerprint Device (AFD) by depositing a poly-silicon film on a large- scale integration wafer. In this process, crys- tals, called grains, form and are randomly dis- tributed. This distribution of grain boundaries, which cannot be changed, is read by a thin film transistor (TFT) and a code is generated. In theory, 40TFTs can provide one trillion num- bers, and the TFT takes up very little space. Alteration and duplication are deemed to be impossible, and no additional cost is necessary. If it becomes standard for interactions between computers, smart cards and r/w devices, the host will have a record of the transaction and can identify whether the card and chip are the same as the one on which the fingerprint was registered 25) . This means that even if data can be copied from a smart card, it will not be of any use for access unless the illegal user also has the original valid smart card to use with the r/w device. This should be especially help-
Vol. 44 No. 8 Access Control Security with Multiple Biometrics Contactless Smart Card 2025ful to network forensic analysis. Unfortunately, we were not able to obtain additional informa- tion from the developers of the AFD that would allow us to devise a specific application based on this very interesting and promising research.6. Proposal Details6.1 The Conctactless Smart CardThe proposal is to use a contactless smart card (CSC) in conjunction with fingerprint; fa- cial and iris biometric features as the next gen- eration multiple purpose ID and access control card. The CSC is recommended due to the advantages of lower mechanical complexity of the r/w unit, thereby affording higher reliabil- ity and less maintenance in the field. The high volume and passenger throughput requirements for public transit fit well with the needs of air- port security and border control systems, where rapid, secure processing is needed.We recommend serious consideration be given to the use of ferroelectric random access mem- ory (FRAM) as the process and memory tech- nology to be used in the next generation CSC ID card. Currently, electronically erasable pro- grammable read only memory (EEPROM) is the primary memory device used to store data in smart cards. However, FRAM is superior to EEPROM in many respects, including a write speed over 10,000 times faster. In addition, FRAM has lower voltage writes than EEPROM and FLASH; consumes about 1/400th of the power EEPROM uses for writing data, and its rewrite endurance is 100,000 times greater 19) . A FRAM-based CSC system with 32 kilobytes of memory will soon be on the market, and could be used to support all of the proposed ID applications7).6.2 A Generic Airport Identification/ Information SystemA near term application for this system could be in support of airport and airline security sys- tems being planned in the US and around the world. A generic outline of one is provided in Fig. 2.A key factor for a secure access control sys- tem is, first and foremost, proper and accurate enrollment procedures as suggested in Fig. 1.The system outlined in Fig. 2 above should be designed and implemented not just for the air- port and airlines, but also with due considera- tion for related organizations like immigrations, customs, law enforcement and intelligence agen- cies. The key elements of the airport informa-Fig. 2AIRPORT INFORMATION SYSTEM Proposed generic airport identity and access control information system. tion system (AIS) in Fig. 2 are the employee and trusted passenger (Pax) databases. The trusted Pax database would contain screened and reg- istered airline Pax data, and interface with the locations where passengers enter and exit the system. That is, check-in counters or kiosks, boarding gates and border control points. The employee database would be more detailed than the Pax database, and could support access control for the full time and contractor person- nel who work at, or perform services in sup- port of the airport and airlines. When autho- rized, airport employee cards could also be used to support secure logical access to various air- port operations information systems like reser- vations, check-in, air traffic control and other key computer systems. Integrating or interfac- ing the AIS databases with outside organiza- tions would ensure that the most recent ter- rorist, criminal and security alert information is available to support passenger and employee checks, and determining the level of security in effect at the airport.The use of multiple biometric features would allow the selection of devices and applications to fit the security, economic and social needs of the specific subsystem and its environment. For example, counter check-in may only require a fingerprint authentication, since the attendant will do the facial check against the photo ID. Kiosk/automated check-in and gates should re- quire at least fingerprint and facial authenti- cation. However, immigration, air traffic con- trol, aircraft maintenance area access verifica- tion may be better served by the higher level of iris scanning security. Therefore, the CSC and its related reader/writer system will need to be able to download various software biometric al-
2026 IPSJ JournalAug. 2003Table 2 Proposed combinations of biometrics templates with contactless smart card ID. IrisCheck-in Counters with Attendants O Check-in kiosk / terminals (un-attended) X Boarding or other automatic gates O Ramp & Runway Areas O Baggage & Freight Areas O Aircraft Maintenance, Support, Services X Border Control X Logical Network Access X Access & Coordination with Outside Agencies       XNote: X — Highly Recommended, O — Suggested Option  Fingerprint  Facial X X X X X X X X X         O X X X X O O O O                 gorithms to support multiple levels of security and access control requirements. Table 2 be- low suggests some of the possible combinations of biometric features with the CSC ID.The selective use of iris scanning and facial recognition should be used to support the grow- ing needs of law enforcement, border security, transportation security, airline passengers and other potential users. The human fingerprint has its problems, but the overall pervasiveness of this feature in law enforcement, military, im- migration and access control systems makes it difficult to ignore or dispense with. Therefore, there is a need to include fingerprint templates in the next generation ID card for compatibil- ity with legacy systems. There are advocates for the use of voice recognition, because people are accustomed to speaking into phones, and there is no intrusive process or physical contact required. However, our proposal is focused on an airport system, and tied to a multiple fea- ture smart card. In the first case, airports are very noisy places. The surroundings include numerous types of public address system an- nouncements, passenger and staff activities and conversations; vehicle sounds and of course jet engines. Voice recognition also often requires some form of online interaction, which would necessitate a large database to match against. This process would take multiple seconds to perform, and might have to be repeated. Con- tactless smart cards can conduct on-card tem- plate authentication in a matter of milliseconds. This rapid processing speed is essential to sup- port passenger throughout, staff efficiency and responsiveness.Secure logical access is important to the prevention of illegal intrusions into databases and supervisory control and data acquisition (SCADA) systems. Access to command of such systems could permit terrorists to control or interfere with the air traffic control systems.Iris scanning, using mini charged couple device (CCD) cameras would be an excellent supple- ment to the existing logical access systems of- fered by the use of passwords and fingerprint readers.Table 2 uses fingerprints instead of hand ge- ometry because of the widespread availability of affordable, compact readers that support not only physical, but also logical network access. Retina scanning and signatures are not included because they are difficult to use in an airport where there is a high level of physical activity, and need for rapid movement of large numbers of personnel.6.3 Statistical Factors for Multiple Biometrics SystemsAs noted in paragraph-4, there is a need to address statistical weakness related to multiple biometrics feature tests 9) . One way is to try to integrate biometrics features and develop a more robust and accurate system. For example, a biometrics system that matches an input (I) against the available template stored in the sys- tem to measure the distance (D) between the input and the template. Depending on the mea- sured distance the system decides which class, T or F the input belongs. Where T indicates the class of genuine user and F indicates class other than the genuine users. This can be ex-pressed as follows:I∈ T (ifD∈R) (1) F (otherwise)Here R is a set that consists of distance mea- sures representing genuine users. Let A1 and A2 be two such biometrics system having false rejection probability α1 and α2 respectively. It is assumed that one can fix α and β of the re- spective systems in such a manner that the indi- vidual system parameterR1 and R2 changes ac- cordingly affecting the performance of the sys- tem. Now we can calculate the overall false re- 
Vol. 44 No. 8 Access Control Security with Multiple Biometrics Contactless Smart Card 2027jection probability α asα = 1−(1−α1)(1−α2)= α1 + α2 − α1α2 (2)So while integrating two such system, we first fix α and corresponding to that α we will get a set of values for α1 and α2 We can now deter- mine the false acceptance probability β. Thus false acceptance probability β is function of α1 and α2. To calculate R1 and R2 we can assume some reasonable probability model for random error (false rejection) or approximate it by a suitable empirical distribution obtained from real or simulated data. Subject to this, we have to minimize the probability of false acceptance β and compute its value. It is not guaranteed that β would be as low as one would like to have. In case computed β turns out to be rea- sonable fix R1 and R2 that corresponds this β. Otherwise, we change the value of α slightly and accordingly recalculate α1 and α2 and ob- serve the value of β. This process can be re- peated for a large number of values of α that is acceptable for practical considerations. Then choose an acceptable combination of α1, α2 and β. This computation will provide R1 and R2 8). However, more work is needed to test the ap- plicability of such a concept.6.4 Proposed Authentication ProcessTo access the system, we propose a stored biometric process. The user places the card on the reader and inputs the biometric feature on a live scan device. The live scan device sends the template and chip AFD to the PC or worksta- tion (WS). The PC/WS authenticates the live scan with the properly enrolled and encrypted template and chip AFD on the smart card. The smart card matches the stored template with the input from the live scans and sends the re- sults, accept or reject, message to the PC or WS. Access is granted or denied.The card is designed not only for logical ac- cess, but also for physical access like the system provided in Fig. 4.6.5 Liveness and Testing CriteriaAs noted in paragraph four, biometric de- vices can be spoofed or fooled using a variety of methods. We have noted some technical de- velopments, which may aid in countering such attacks in paragraph five, but the key factors are likely to remain proper enrollment and live- ness testing. Liveness testing is based on three general categories: 1) intrinsic properties of a living body, 2) involuntary signals generated byFig. 3User verification for PC or workstation logical access.  Fig. 4Smart card use for physical and logical access control.a living body, 3) responses to a stimulus by a living body (challenge – response) 29).Our proposal seeks to minimize the effective- ness of artificial or simulated biometrics mimics or substitutes by combining biometric features to be tested with other authentication meth- ods. This is demonstrated in Table 2 and Fig. 3 and Fig.4. Our proposal uses something the person has, in this case, a CSC combined with something the system will know, the CSC’s chip AFD identity. More research is needed into the nature of how the chips AFD can be read and secured for use by live scan devices. We also recommend the continued use of manned su- pervision at key locations like the enrollment points. There should also be manned backup to allow human intervention at check-in coun- ters and border control points to resolve any authentication failures by automatic means.7. DiscussionJapan’s Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport (MLIT) plans to conduct a trial us- ing contactless integrated circuit (IC) chips and biometrics technologies to help speed up the check in time at Japanese airports. This may begin in early 2003 at Narita Airport. The trial will use 1,000 participants from Japan Airlines
2028 IPSJ Journal Aug. 2003Systems’ frequent flyers. The participants will register their passport information, face recog- nition data and iris recognition data at enroll- ment. Passport information will be put on the IC chip, which will be embedded in either a mo- bile phone strap or a card the participants will carry with them.At check-in, a passenger’s passport informa- tion is read from the contactless IC chip and a facial recognition device confirms the pas- senger matches the individual data stored in the chip. After authentication is completed, an automated check-in terminal issues a board- ing pass and the passenger proceeds to a se- curity gate. The IC chip and a positive iris match permit the passenger to go through the security gate 17) . This application is very close to our proposal in Table 2 related to unat- tended check-in and boarding gate procedures. It would also be very pragmatic to use the contactless smart card to support the traveler registration since these are also used on many types of public transit in Japan. A contactless visa document would also work well in the re- verse situation of verifying the person entering a country on a visa is the same person it was issued to.New York’s John F. Kennedy (JFK) Interna- tional Airport has initiated a pilot iris scanning technology pro ject to prevent employee secu- rity breaches. JFK is testing the technology on about 300 employees in its Terminal 4. This is related to access control for secure areas like the customs area leading to the runway/tarmac 18) . This pilot reflects our proposal in Table 2 re- lated to access to secure areas like ramps, run- ways, baggage areas and computer rooms with access to other organizations. This could be easily extended to support secure logical access once the employee is in the secure computer area.We are aware that there may be disagreement with the proposed use of fingerprints through- out Table 2 above. This may be the result of cultural, organizational or individual pref- erences. For example, in Japan, there is op- position to fingerprinting due to its association with former alien registration practices. Also, in many countries of the world, fingerprinting is associated with police and criminal activ- ities, and has negative implications for some people. However, there are many legacy sys- tems in place, and a wide range of applications and products that support fingerprint recogni-tion. The two major ID programs scheduled for implementation in the US, the DOD’s CAC and the TSA’s TWIC, are likely to use finger- prints as part of their biometrics 24),28) . The US must also select biometric feature(s) for its new visa process mandated by the Border Security Act (S.1794), which is officially termed the En- hanced Border Security and Visa Reform Act. This law requires the State Department to issue machine-readable visas with biometric identi- fiers, and for the Justice Department to deploy readers. One of the biometrics may be finger- prints 22) . This may lead to a wider degree of usage, enrollment and database creation based on fingerprint biometrics. For these reasons, we have listed fingerprints as highly recommended in Table 2 to assure the system we are proposing will be compatible with the major US ID sys- tems. Persons who cannot provide acceptable fingerprints could substitute an iris template. The final fallback is always human intervention and confirmation.8. SummaryThe paper has noted the environment in the US is calling for increased security at airports. This has created a search for improved identi- fication and access control measures. The pa- per has looked at the smart card and biomet- ric technologies that may be able to meet these needs. None of the solutions are perfect, and the paper has identified issues related to the use of smart cards and biometrics. Figure 1 offers some solutions to the threat of artificial fingerprints. Figures 2 – 4 outline a generic air- port identity and access control system to im- prove airport security. Table 2 proposes how to combine biometric features with contactless smart cards to implement the improved access control system outlined in Fig.2. The paper does not advocate eliminating human interface and contact with passengers. There should still be guards, inspectors and airline employees in the system that can scrutinize and assess sus- picious or unusual behavior. However, it does propose technical methods to support and im- prove physical and logical access security.9. Future ResearchThere is a need for additional research on each of the subsystems in the generic outline presented in Fig. 2 above. These subsystems must be capable of fully integrated operations at the database level to provide an overall con-
Vol. 44 No. 8 Access Control Security with Multiple Biometrics Contactless Smart Card 2029tribution to the larger requirements of Home- land Security and counter terrorist operations. This leads to the need for more work on statis- tical analysis, interoperability, cooperation and coordination, all of which are suitable topics for continuing research and implementation.References1) Akin, D.: Customs Set to Use Iris Scans at Airports, http://www.iridiantech.com/news. php (2002).2) Anderson, R.J.: Security Engineering—A Guide to Building Dependable Distributed Sys- tems, Wiley (2001).3) Anderson, R.J. and Skorobogatov, S.: Optical Fault Induction Attacks, http://www.ftp.cl. cam.ac.uk/ftp/users.rja14/faultpap3.pdf (2002).4) Baker,D.A.:PentagonEndorsesBiometricsto Enhance Computer Security, http:// nationaldefense.ndia.org/article.cfm?Id=521 (2002).5) Blackburn, D., Bone, M. and Phillips, P.J.: Facial Recognition Vendor Test 2000, http:// www.frvt.org/DLs/FRVT 2000.pdf (2001).6) Bone, M. and Crumbacker, C.: Facial Recog- nition — Assessing Its Viability in the Correc- tions Environment, http://frvt.org/DLs/ FRVT2.pdf (2001).7) Cubic Security: http://www.cubic.com/CSD/ go-card.htm (2001).8) Das, T. and Roy, B.: Informal Proposal on the Use of Multiple Biometrics by the Indian Sta- tistical Institute, Cryptology Research Group, Kolkata, India, http://www.isical.ac.in (2003).9) Daugman,J.:CombiningMultipleBiometrics, http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/users/jgd1000/ combine/combine.html10) IBM Nederland: http://www.ibm.com.news/ nl/20022604 nl nl ibm looks airline securityin the eye.html (2002).11) Jesorsky, O., Frischolz, R.W. and Kirchberg,K.J.: Robust Face Detection Using the Haus- dorff Distance, Proc. 3rd International Confer- ence on Audio and Video-based Biometric Per- son Authentication, Lecture Notes in Computer Science, LNCS-2091, Springer-Verlag, pp.90– 95, Berlin, Heidelberg, New York (2001).12) Karlin, S.: Smart Cards, Widely Used in Eu- rope, Migrate to United States, http://www. spectrum.ieee.org/spectrum/mar/02/ departments/ncard.html (2002).13) Knight, W.: Camera Flash Opens Up Smart Cards, http://newscientist.com/news/print. jsp?id=ns99992273 (2002).14) Kocher, R.W.: Biometrics and the Common Access Card (CAC), http://c3i.osd.mil/biometrics/ (2002).15) Liu, S. and Silverman, M.: A Practical Guideto Biometric Security Technology, http:// computer.org/itpro/homepage/Jan Feb01/ security3.htm (2001).16) Matsumoto, T., Matsumoto, H., Hoshino, S. and Yamada, K.: Impact of Artificial Gummy Fingers on Fingerprint Systems, http://www. spie.org/Conferences/Programs/02/pw/conds /4677.html (2002).17) Miyake, K.: Japan to Test Biometrics for Air- port Check-in, http://www.itworld.com/sec/ 2054/021106japanbio/pfindex.html.18) Philadelphia Inquirer: Iris-recognition Being Used in Airports, Refugee Camps, http://www. siliconvalley.com/mld.siliconvalley/news/ editorial/4456904.htm (2002).19) Ramtron: Ramtron and Fujitsu to Jointly Develop Advanced 0.35 Micron FRAM Mem- ory Process, http://www.ramtron/com/news/ (2001).20) Sahbi, H. and Boujenaa, N.: Robust Face Recognition Using Dynamic Space Warping, Lecture Notes In Computer Science, LNCS- 2359, Springer-Verlag, Berlin, Heidelberg, New York (2002).21) Smart Card Alliance: Smart Cards and Bio- metrics in Privacy-Sensitive Secure Personal Identification System, http://www. smartcardalliance.org (2002).22) Strickland, L.S. and Willard, J.: Reengineer- ing the Immigration System: A Case for Data Mining and Information Assurance to Enhance Homeland Security, http://www. homelandsecurity.org/journal/Articles/ displayacrticle.asp?article=75 (2002).23) Tisratelli, M., Lagorio, A. and Grosso, E.: Understanding Iconic Image-Based Face Bio- metrics, Lecture Notes in Computer Science, LNCS-2359, Springer-Verlag, Berlin, Heidel- berg, New York (2002).24) Vanderhoof, R.: President’s Letter May 2002, http://www.caffeine.ieee.org?INST/mar02/ ffinger.html (2002).25) Vonverheid, E.: Artificial Fingerprints-on-a- Chip Could Discourage Computer Crime, http://www.caffeine.ieee.org?INST/mar02/ ffinger.html (2002).26) Wilson, C.: Get Smart: The Emergence of Smart Cards in the United States and Their Pivotal Role in Internet Commerce, pp.89–90, Mullaney Publishing Group (2001).27) Woodward, J.D., Webb, K.W., Newton, E.M., Bradley, M. and Rubenson, D.: Army Biomet- rics Applications: Identifying and Addressing Sociocultural Concerns, http://www.rand.org/ publications/MR/MR1237 (2001).           
2030 IPSJ JournalAug. 200328) Woodward, J.D.: Biometrics — Facing Up to Terrorism, http://www.rand/org/organization /ard/ (2001).29) Woodward, J.D., Orlans, Nicholas, Higgins and Peter, T.: Biometrics; Identity Assur- ance in the Information Age, p.142, McGraw- Hill/Osborne, NewYork (2003).(Received November 29, 2002) (Accepted June 3, 2003)Michael W. David has a B.A. 1970 and a B.S. Industrial Engineering, 1971, from Lehigh University, Pa. He also has an M.S. in Systems Management from the University of South- ern California (USC), 1975. Hestudied Japanese at the Defense Language In- stitute and the Foreign Service Institute from 1977–1979. Mr. David is a graduate of the Stanford Graduate School of Business Execu- tive Program, 1992, and has attended Cryptog- raphy courses at MIT and ETH. He served on active duty in the US Army from 1971–1981, and in the Army Reserve from 1981–1999. Ac- tive service in Korea, Okinawa and Japan. Re- tired rank, Lieutenant Colonel. Last reserve position, Assistant Chief of Staff for Political- Military Affairs, US Army Japan. Mr. David is currently Vice President, International Busi- ness Development Cubic Corporation, Hqs., San Diego, Ca. (1982–Present). Cubic’s indus- trial products are related to automatic fare col- lection systems for public transit systems. Mil- itary product lines include air and ground com- bat training systems, electronic warfare, com- munication surveillance, secure ID and access control systems. He is a member of IEEE; ACM; IACR, Armed Forces Communications and Electronic Association; Association of Old Crows; Japan Military History Society.Kouichi Sakurai received the B.S. degree in mathematics from Faculty of Science, Kyushu University and the M.S. degree in applied science from Faculty of Engineering, Kyushu Univer- sity in 1986 and 1988, respec-tively. He had been engaged in the research and development on cryptography and information security at Computer & Information Systems Laboratory at Mitsubishi Electric Corporation from 1988 to 1994. He received the Dr. de- gree in engineering from Faculty of Engineer- ing, Kyushu University in 1993. Since 1994 he has been working for Department of Computer Science of Kyushu University as an associate professor, and now he is a full professor from 2002. His current research interests are in cryp- tography and information security. Dr. Saku- rai is a member of the Information Processing Society of Japan, the Mathematical Society of Japan, ACM and the International Association for Cryptologic Research.   