Vol. 44 No. 8 IPSJ Journal Aug. 2003Regular PaperReflective Probabilistic Packet Marking Scheme for IP TracebackNobuhiko Nishio,†1,†2 Noriyuki Harashima†3 and Hideyuki Tokuda†4This paper describes the design and implementation of Reflective Probabilistic Packet Mark- ing (RPPM) scheme, which is a traceback scheme against distributed denial-of-service (DDoS) attacks. Attacks include traffic laundered by reflectors which are sent false requests by at- tackers posing as a victim. Reflectors are among the hardest security problems on today’s Internet. One promising solution to tracing the origin of attacks, the probabilistic packet marking (PPM) scheme, has proposed. However, conventional PPM cannot work against reflector attacks — reflector problem. Also, it encodes a mark into IP Identification field, this disables the use of ICMP — encoding problem. RPPM is a solution to both the reflector and encoding problem. We have extended PPM to render reflectors ineffectual by reflecting marking statistics of incoming packets at reflectors in order to trace the origin of the attacks. Furthermore, we have encoded a mark into the IP option field without reducing necessary information. Thus, RPPM can traceback beyond reflectors, ensures ICMP-compatibility, and eliminates possibility of failure in attack path reconstruction. Simulation results and our implementation based on Linux demonstrated that RPPM retains the semantics of conven- tional PPM on a path between an attacker and a reflector, and its performance is feasible for practice.1. IntroductionDenial-of-service (DoS) attacks are still a ma- jor threat to the Internet and becoming more serious. Attackers are increasingly creating au- tomated attack tools with faster deployment than ever before1). In DoS attacks, an at- tacker floods target remote machines or net- works with false requests to consume their re- sources, thereby denying or degrading service to legitimate users. A recent observation re- ported over 12,000 attacks against more than 5,000 distinct targets, ranging from well-known e-commerce companies such as Amazon and Hotmail to small foreign ISPs and dial-up con- nections 2).DoS attack is a serious problem and diffi- cult to prevent, because the attackers use in- correct, or “spoofed” source addresses in the attack packets, concealing the real origin of the attacks. Unfortunately, two characteristics of the Internet allows such anonymous packets: no entity ensures that the source address is correct and no mechanism traces a path back†1 Graduate School of Media and Governance, Keio University†2 “Intelligent Cooperation and Control”, PRESTO, Japan Science and Technology Corporation (JST)†3 ACCESS Co., LTD.†4 Faculty of Environmental Information, Keio Univer-sityto the origin. One approach to prevent DoS attacks is to eliminate the capability to forge the source address. One example of this ap- proach is a filtering technique called ingress fil- tering 3) which blocks packets that arrive with illegitimate source address. The effectiveness of ingress filtering depends on universal deploy- ment of itself. Furthermore, forged source ad- dress are legitimately used by network address translators (NATs), Mobile-IP, and various uni- directional link technologies. As the other ex- ample of this preventive approach, IPsec would be considered, if it is deployed all over the In- ternet. However, since IPsec is originally devel- oped for authentication and data encryption, IPsec itself could not prevent DoS attack com- pletely, even if it is universally deployed. Gen- erally, for data encryption IPsec uses IKE for key exchange, and SYN packet at this time can easily lead to DoS attacks ☆ . Here, we have to clarify that we do not dare to deny any of con- tributions of this kind of approach for DoS at- tack. On the contrary, we insist that we should apply multiple techniques of different approach collaboratively against DoS attacks. In this we  1848☆Some may insists that routers should authenticate IPsec’s AH before forwarding packets to servers by dispatching all the clients’ public key to the router. It is essentially the same as ingress filter’s technique and much worse in performance due the heavy to encryption processing.
Vol. 44 No. 8 Reflective Probabilistic Packet Marking Scheme for IP Traceback 1849mean we have to form a kind of multiple safety net. Therefore, we go for another approach — tracing a path back to the origin. This ap- proach is quite different from the preventive one mentioned above. This approach is applied af- ter attacks happened for its traceback and this also need universal deployment over the Inter- net for packet marking☆.Circumstances are worsened by further com- plicated distributed denial-of-service (DDoS) attacks due to use of reflectors 4),5). That is, at- tackers first locate a very large number of reflec- tors, which can be any Internet servers. Then they send the reflectors forged traffic, purport- edly coming from a particular host: the victim. The reflectors will in turn generate reply traffic to the victim. The net result is that the flood at the victim arrives from numerous reflectors. Consequently, such reflector attacks also should be considered as a challenge of traceback tech- nologies.Although many traceback techniques have been proposed, they have significant weaknesses that limit their usability in practice. One promising solution, the probabilistic packet marking (PPM) scheme 6) allows routers to probabilistically mark packets with partial path information during packet forwarding. The victim can then reconstruct the attack paths after receiving an estimated number of pack- ets. However, we found the conventional PPM scheme cannot work under reflector attacks, and its encoding is incompatible with ICMP.In this research, Reflective Probabilistic Packet Marking (RPPM) scheme, which is a traceback scheme against DDoS attacks includ- ing traffic laundered by reflectors, has been de- signed and implemented. We have extended the PPM scheme to render reflectors ineffec- tual by reflecting marking statistics of incom- ing packets at reflectors in order to trace the origin beyond the reflectors. Simulation results have shown this extension retains the seman- tics of conventional PPM scheme on a path be- tween an attacker and a reflector. At the same time, we have encoded a mark into the IP op- tion field without eliminating necessary infor- mation. This ensured that our scheme is ICMP-☆ This requirement of universal deployment would be gradually regarded as an inevitable one, especially for such hosts that have global IP address and pro- vide some services out to the Internet, considering the recent trends like various security patches are issued almost every day.Fig. 1Reflector attack.                                     compatible and eliminates possibility of failure in path reconstruction.The remainder of this paper is organized in the following. Reflector attack, which is one of the most difficult DoS attacks, is explained in Section 2. Section 3 describes preceding trace- back techniques against DoS attacks and com- pares them in order to lead our design space. In Section 4, the reflector problem and encod- ing problem on the conventional PPM are ad- dressed, and the design of RPPM scheme is de- scribed as a solution to these problems. Our practical implementation based on Linux is ex- plained in Section 5, and its effectiveness and performance are shown in Section 6. Finally, we discuss our future work in Section 7 and con- clude this paper in Section 8.2. Reflector AttackMost common DoS attacks use IP spoofing, where attackers forge or spoof the source ad- dress of each packet they send, thereby conceal- ing their location and disabling an effective re- sponse. IP spoofing can also be used to make an innocent third-party “reflect” the attack. This attack, called reflector attack, is known as the hardest DoS attack in today’s Internet 1),4)∼6). Figure 1 depicts reflector attacks. One host, the master attacker, manipulates compromised slaves in remote and make slaves “launder” at- tacks by sending a packet spoofed with a vic- tim’s address to numerous reflectors. As a re- sult, those numerous reflectors sends responses back towards the victim. The reflectors can be any Internet server, especially DNS servers and Gnutella servers are warned.In reflector attacks, note that individual re- flector sends at a much lower rate compared to 
1850 IPSJ Journal Aug. 2003attackers flooding the victim directly, becauseeach slave can diffuse the flooding. Supposethere are Ns slaves and Nrf reflectors. In gen-eral, Ns < Nrf because the attacker can simplyuse reflectors by sending packets, whereas theattacker still needs to crack slaves to manipu-late them. Assuming a flooding rate F comingfrom each slave, each reflector would generatea indirect flooding rate of Frf = Ns F. This Nrfindicates that slaves can reduce indirect flood- ing rate rather than direct flooding rate, hence they can conceal the attacks easier. In addi- tion, the flooding rate of modern DDoS attacks is various. For example, a new DDoS method discovered by Asta 7) , called zombie pulsing at- tack, directs short burst of traffic to targets. The variety of flooding rate also increases the complexity of reflector attacks.For these reasons, the reflector attack is a se- rious and difficult problem. It should be dealt without loss of time, thus we address tracing the origin of DDoS attacks beyond reflectors.3. Related WorkOver the past few years, traceback techniques against DoS attacks using IP spoofing have re- ceived considerable attention. Early traceback technique is known as testing network links at routers by input debugging. Furthermore, Burch developed the link testing concept to a novel system that automatically floods can- didate network links and traces the origin of attacks 8) . However, these approaches cannot work after an attack has completed. In order to trace after an attack has completed, trace- back system should store information of the at- tack paths in particular space. There are two approaches for such storing: end-host approach and infrastructure approach.The end-host approach attempts to distribute the information of the attack paths in pack- ets and collects them at end-hosts. It is ex- plored in ITRACE proposed by Bellovin9),10), which lets each routers send ICMP messages to an end-host with a very low probability. Af- ter the end-host receives a sufficient number of packets, it can reconstruct the path of pack- ets traversed. One promising scheme in the end-host approach, Savage proposed the proba- bilistic packet marking (PPM) scheme 6) . PPM scheme enables marking partial information of path at routers with static length field. How- ever, the PPM scheme increases computationalcomplexity as the number of slaves increases. Song proposed an advanced PPM scheme 11) by use of the network maps 12),13) for reducing such computation overhead. The advantage of these end-host approaches is that once deployed, the managing cost becomes very low, because only end-hosts attempt to infer attack paths.In contrast, the infrastructure approach at- tempts to store information of attack paths in the network infrastructure. Stone proposed an overlay network and achieved efficient log- ging 14). Also Snoeren proposed Source Path Isolation Engine (SPIE) 15) which enhanced routers to maintain a packet digest for for- warded traffic. Since SPIE uses a large set of hash function in generating a packet digest, SPIE can traceback the origin in detail. Ac- cording to SPIE, the advantage of the infras- tructure approach is robustness under low vol- ume flow (even a single packet), because it can diffuse the path information into a broad in- frastructure. This characteristic is important when considering reflector attacks whose traffic volume of each attack path may be low.However, even with these preceding trace- back techniques, the reflector attack problem still remains unsolved. Since the reflector loses a mark information, the end-host approach could not deal with reflector attack. We de- scribe the detail of this problem in Section 4.3. Also the inftrastructure approach could not re- gard the reflected traffic as transformed traffic, and it dismisses to trace this transformed traf- fic. Moreover, the infrastructure approach is expensive to manage widely distributed system rather than the end-host approach.Consequently, we consider that the end-host approach has usability and potential ability to deal with reflector attack, however, the end- host approach has yet to be developed in prac- tice. Therefore, we address our design space to traceback by the end-host approach.4. Reflective Probabilistic Packet Marking SchemeIn this section, we present the design of Re- flective Probabilistic Packet Marking (RPPM) scheme. RPPM is a traceback scheme which adopts the end-host approach and can work un- der DDoS attacks including traffic laundered by reflectors. We first set the goal and assump- tions, then explain the two limitation of the existence PPM scheme: reflector problem and encoding problem. Next we show the solutions 
Vol. 44 No. 8 Reflective Probabilistic Packet Marking Scheme for IP Traceback 1851to these problems. Finally, we describe the de- tail of three algorithms, which can deal with reflector attacks: marking, reflection, and re- construction algorithms.4.1 The GoalIdeally, traceback system should be able to identify a real source of packets, even if the source attempted to conceal their address by spoofing at random or using reflectors. At the same time, the traceback system should ensure backward compatibility. In traceback, we are interested in constructing attack paths, where the path consists of each router traversed by the packet on its journey from an attacker (either a master or a slave) to the victim. Also there are multiple source attacks, the traceback system should reconstruct an attack graph which is the tree of aggregated paths rooted by the victim.Figure 2 illustrates an attack graph as viewed by a victim V. Every potential at- tack origin Ai is a leaf in a directed acyclic graph rooted at V , and every router Ri and reflector Rfi are internal nodes along a path of some A and V. The attack path from Ai is the unique ordered list of routers and reflectors between Ai and V. For instance, {A2, R2, R3, R4, V } is the attack path spoofed at random and {A4, R6, Rf1, R4, V } is the at- tack path using reflectors.To simplify the traceback problem, we groups masters and slaves in Fig. 1 as attackers. The detection or prevention of the path among at- tackers currently relies on other existing tech- nologies 16)∼18) .4.2 AssumptionsSince the design space of traceback is large, we set the following assumptions to constrain our design space:• an attacker can generate any packets, • multiple attackers may conspire,• attackers may be aware they are being traced,• an attacker can use a reflector on each path, • attackers may send a large number of pack-ets during attacks,• routers may subvert, but not often,• the route between an attacker and a victimis fairly stable.The first four assumptions are obvious char-acteristics of attacks that are restricted by the nature of the Internet. Hence, attackers can also generate a mark when they send packets, and multiple attack paths can exist with spoof- ing at random or using reflector.The remaining assumptions constrain our de- sign but need additional discussions. First, we assume that an attacker will send numer- ous packets to degrade the target service per- formance during attacks. Similar to the con- ventional PPM scheme, our scheme relies on this assumption, because we probabilistically let routers mark a partial information of the at- tack path and a victim collects packets to recon- struct an attack graph. Although the flooding rate of reflector attack is less than typical at- tack, the total amount of packet during attacks (that is more than an hour to keep system de- grade) is still a large number. Our scheme needs only a hundred packets to reconstruct each at- tack path, sufficient for such attack. With re- gard to a single packet DoS attack, such as ping- of-death 19) , this assumption may not hold.Second, although an attack graph may con- tain false positives in the presence of subverted routers, we separate with a path validation is- sue from traceback problem. The path valida- tion issue is discussed more in Section 7.1. Ac- tually, most network administrators disable the accessibility from anonymous hosts to routers, it is scarcely considered that routers will be at the disposal of attackers.Finally, while instability of Internet routing is well-known20), we assume its changes ex- tremely rare for short duration of time. By this assumption, the traceback system should shortly finish inferring an attack graph, there- fore if any short-term collected packets match, it can be regard as traversed same path.4.3 Limitation of PPMThe basic idea of the PPM scheme is that routers probabilistically write some encoding of partial path information into the packets dur- ing forwarding. This scheme reserves two static fields of the size of IP address, start and end,                                                                  Fig. 2An attack graph of containing two attack paths. The dotted arrows indicates attack path.
1852IPSJ Journal Aug. 2003                                                                                                                    Fig. 3A reflected attack path forwarded by the application layer on the reflector.High false positivesAs d further, Sd increases. However, the number of packets marked by each router decreases, thus the combination Ψd cannot be identified uniquely.High computation complexityAs d further, Sd increases. Therefore a large number of Ψd combination needs to check.Low efficiency of collecting marksIt cannot distinguish a packet whether it ismarked or not.Song uses a large hash space to avoid acollision among numerous routers and en-codes a hash ID into IP Identification field,and a static distance field in each packet. Each router updates these fields as the following: each router marks the packet with a probability p. When the router decides to mark the packet, it writes its own IP address into the start field and zero into the distance field. Otherwise, if the distance field is already zero, indicating its previous router marked the packet, it writes its own IP address into the end field, representing the edge between its previous routers and it- self. Finally, if the router does not mark the packet, it always increments the distance field. Thus the distance field in the packet indicates the number of routers the packet has traversed from the router which marked the packet to the victim.However, the conventional PPM has two main problems in practice: reflector problem and encoding problem.4.3.1 Reflector ProblemSince a reflector is not a router, received pack- ets sent by attackers arrive at application layer on the reflector. As shown in Fig. 3, while the PPM scheme marks routers’ addresses between the attacker and the reflector, mark information is lost if the reflector processes packets at appli- cation layer and reply to a victim as a new IP flow. Thus it impedes a traceback between at- tacker and reflector. The solution to this prob- lem is described in Section 4.4.4.3.2 Encoding ProblemConventional PPM scheme encodes a markinto IP Identification field in the IP header. Inorder to use the 16-bit IP identification field,it divides each router’s address with some re-dundancy check into k fragments. Let Ψd andSd denote the set of fragment marked with adistance d and the set of router at d respec-tively. As a result, the computing complexitythereby reducing computing complexity asof checking combination of fragmented packetshead, it relies on the assumption that the victim has the Internet map12) of upstream routers. Assuming the reflector attacks, such map should contain all the reflectors’ upstream routers. However, its managing cost is too ex- pensive.One problem with changing IP Identification field is that disables IP reassembly function. Preceding schemes ignore this problem based on recent measurements which suggest only less than 0.25% of packets are fragmented 21).Finally, the most serious problem is that changing the IP Identification field disables the use of ICMP. ping and traceroute com- mand sends ICMP Echo and receives ICMP Echo Reply, however, it cannot recognize the reply if IP Identification field has changed. Consequently, disabling ICMP has harmful in- fluence for such network administrating com- mand, therefore the marking scheme should not modify IP Identification field. The solution to this problem is described in Section 4.5.4.4 Solution to the Reflector ProblemOne solution to the problem with a reflector losing a mark is to copy the mark from request to reply. For this copy, the reflector in Fig.3 should capture the marked request packets at the network layer and preserve them. Then the reflector should also reflect the preserved mark into reply packets at network layer, hence the copying marks could be achieved.Note the number of packets between request and reply is asymmetric. For instance on HTTP, a number of packets in GET request message is small, but those in reply message may be large. For this reason, simple marking copy cannot apply such asymmetric connection.is O(  SdΨk). However, in the case of DDoS ddattacks, this scheme has the following problems.O(  SdΨd) 11). For reducing computing over- d
Vol. 44 No. 8 Reflective Probabilistic Packet Marking Scheme for IP Traceback 1853One possible method is use of a formula thatcan expect the number of packets needed to re-construct the path bounded by ln(d) given p(1−p)d−1by Savage 6). Then the reflector simply collects each mark and copies them by weighting with the formula. The advantage of this method is that the number of reflected mark could be the- oretic, therefore the reconstruction at a victim might be easier. However, if reflector cannot re- ceive the sufficient number of packets, the prob- ability distribution between before and after re- flection might be significantly different, there- fore the victim may fail to infer.Alternatively, we let a reflector generate statistics for each mark, then the reflector can copy the mark in accordance with that statis- tics. Since the reflector should distinguish reply and request packets to generate such statistics and reflect a mark, the reflector should track the upper layer protocols not the network layer. Smoothing time series behavior of col- lected packet countSimilar to the retransmission timeout calcu- lation in TCP 22) , we use exponential smooth- ing 23) to reduce irregularities in time series be- havior of packet count. Let t and Y (t) denote the time domain and the observation for at time series data of packet count respectively. Expo- nential smoothing generates an estimate S(t) from the new observation Y (t) and the old esti- mate S(t−1) with a fraction α called smoothing constant. In practice, S(t) is calculated recur- sively in the following fashion.S(t) = αY (t) + (1 − α)S(t − 1) (1) Bowerman stated that the smoothing constant between 0.01 to 0.3 usually worked quite well in practice 24). In our experience, the smoothing constant α = 0.3 was the best value.Furthermore, as we mentioned in Section 2, the flooding rate of DDoS attacks is various. Hence, the sampling period T of statistics needs to calculate for exponential smoothing. Since S(t) is the positive integer for our scheme, if assumed P as the necessary precision number, then the sampling period of statistics should be chosen as αY (t) > 10P . Let F denote the flood- ing rate per second, it leads αT F p(1 − p)d−1 > 10P . Consequently, the recommended T can be represented as following.10PT > αFp(1 − p)d−1 (2)Ifα=0.3,P =2,F =1000,p=0.05,d=10,Fig. 4Format of IP option RPPM.                                                                    the sampling period of statistics should be more than 11 seconds.The valuable T can make appropriate reflec- tion at reflector for any rate of DDoS attack. For example, assuming short burst of traffic, such as zombie pulsing attack, statistics can moderate the irregularities of packet marking.4.5 Solution to the Encoding ProblemTo ensure the backward compatibility, we propose using IP option for packet marking. Al- though preceding schemes dismissed IP option approach as a poor choice due to the expense of appending additional data on flight, it is ob- vious that practical functionality is important over performance. Actually, we consider our approach scarcely degrades the system by the following reasons:• most routers have become powerful enough to process IP options,• it is extremely rare that IP option are used (e.g., ping with IP Record Route op- tion 25)).For these reasons, we designed an IP option Reflective Probabilistic Packet Marking (IP op- tion RPPM) as shown in Fig. 4. The first byte type is divided into three internal fields: a 1-bit cp flag, a 2-bit class field, and a 5-bit number field. The cp flag indicates whether the individ- ual option should be copied into the IP header of the fragments. To reduce the overhead, we defined 0 in order not to copy. The class field groups related options and we choose most gen- eral class control defined 0. In the number field, we arbitrarily defined a new number 28. The second byte is len field, that covers the type, len, and remaining bytes. In our scheme, it is statically 12. The third byte has not yet defined and simply used for IP header padding, thus this 8-bit fields can be defined for extensional flags. The remaining bytes of static distance, start, and end field are used for a marking al- gorithm described in Section 4.6.The advantage of using the IP option field is listed as follows. 
1854IPSJ Journal Aug. 2003  Marking procedure at Router R and Reflector Rf : for each packet wlet x be a random number from [0..1) if x<p thenwrite R into w.start and 0 into w.distance elseif w.distance = 0 then write R into w.end increment w.distance  Fig. 5 Marking algorithm.to mark any more can be considered. However, an attacker can also generate the reflection flags by assumptions; such optimization may disable PPM. From this consideration, the presence of reflector should not change the semantics of marking algorithm. In general, each mark in packet should be overwritten in equal probabil- ity even if any extension might be proposed.4.6.2 Reflection AlgorithmFigure 6 describes the reflection algorithm. The reflection is conducted on a reflector, which can be any Internet server. The reflection algo- rithm has two procedures: storing and reflect- ing. These two procedures share statistics of hash table H. The storing procedure slots in an incoming request packet into H keyed by its source address. Identically marked packets are put into the identical hash entry, then the to- tal count of received packets are incremented. To copy the probability distribution of marks, the reflecting procedure marks an outgoing re- ply packet where its source address and the en- try of H matches. Also the reflecting procedure smoothes H by timer T of sampling period.In this algorithm, it is necessary to distin- guish request and reply packets to generate statistics. To separate packets into request and reply, connection tracking technique is re- quired. Most existing filtering architectures provide such connection tracking feature, we do not refer it here.4.6.3 Reconstruction AlgorithmFigure 7 describes the reconstruction algo- rithm. As we mentioned in Section 4.6.1, skip- ping reconstruction of the path between a re- flector and a victim is efficient. However, the use of explicit flags to decide marking may change the semantics of PPM allowing mali- cious improper use by attackers. For this rea- son, we simply infer potential reflectors from received packets. That is, if the source addressBackward compatibilityIt does not disturb ICMP.No reassemble process of fragmented packetsThe computation complexity is reduced to         O( d Sd).Capability of distinguishing marked packetsThe efficiency of collecting packet at a re-flector or a victim is facilitated.A problem pointed out by Snoeren is that each byte of additional overhead reduces sys- tem bandwidth by approximately 1% in an av- erage packet size of approximately 128-byte 15) . Although our scheme adds 12-byte per packet, not all the packets need to be marked. This indicates the bandwidth consumption can be controlled by the probability p. For example, if assumed the average distance d to the origin is 16 (this is median value measured by Skit- ter26)) and the marking probability p is 0.01, the probability of packet marked at any routers is 1 − (1 − p)d = 0.05, thus system overheadcould be reduced to approximately 0.6%. Another possible problem is the situation when an attacker generate a packet filled with other IP options and leaving no space to mark. By assumption, we separated path validation issue from traceback problem and only assumes anonymous packets, therefore we forced a mark to be overwritten even if other options exists. One way to avoid this problem is to “reserve” the path as well as RSVP 27), allowing innocent senders to signal each router not to mark. Wediscuss this more in Section 7.1.4.6 RPPM AlgorithmsHereunder, we describe the detail of RPPM algorithm consisting of the following three al- gorithms: marking, reflection, and reconstruc- tion.4.6.1 Marking AlgorithmFigure 5 describes the marking algorithm. The marking is conducted on a router and re- flector. The reflector should execute this mark- ing algorithm after the reflection algorithm de- scribed in Section 4.6.2. The basic behavior is nearly equal to conventional PPM.Since neither source nor destination address of a path from a reflector to victim is forged, it is efficient not to mark any more at the down- stream routers from the reflector in this algo- rithm. Accordingly, further optimization that defines the explicit reflection flag to decide not    
Vol. 44 No. 8 Reflective Probabilistic Packet Marking Scheme for IP Traceback 1855                    let T be a timer of sampling periodlet H be a hashtablelet mark be tuples(start, end, distance, count), which is an attribute of a packetlet entry in H be tuples (address, marks, to- tal count)Storeing procedure at Reflector Rf :for each incomming request packet w if H contains w.source thenlet e be an entry(w.destination) in Hincrement e.total count if w.mark thenif H contains w.source thenlet e be an entry(w.source) in H if e.mark = w.markincrement e.mark.count elseput entry(w.source, w.mark, 0) into H Reflecting procedure at Reflector Rf :for each outgoing reply packet w if H contains w.source thenlet e be an entry(w.destination) in H if T expired thenexp smoothing(total count of e)exp smoothing(each count of e.marks) reset Tlet x be a random number from [0..e.total count)select mark m from x in marking statis- ticsPath reconstruction procedure at vicitim V : let G be a tree with root Vlet edges in G be tuples (start, end, distance) let H be a hashtablelet entries in H be tuples (reflector, distance) for each packet w from attackerif w.start = w.source thenput entry(w.start, w.distance) into Hif w.distance = 0 theninsert edge(w.start, V , 0) into Gelseinsert edge(w.start, w.end, w.distance)into Gremove any edge(x, y, d)with d ̸= distance from x to V in G extract path(Ri..Rj)by enumeratin acyclic path in Gshow all entries(reflector, distance) in H           Fig. 7Reconstruction algorithm.                                                  if m ̸= NULLwrite m into w.{start,end,distance}Fig. 6 Reflection algorithm.Fig. 8Implementation of RPPM.    set of hook points called table can be defined. We select the following four hook points as traceback table in IPv4 layer: PRE ROUTING (after IP checksum calculation, before rout- ing), LOCAL IN (when an incoming packet is destined for a local process), LOCAL OUT (when an outgoing packet is created locally), and POST ROUTING (any outgoing packet after rout- ing).   and the start field of mark are identical, such packet is reflected by the reflector. Note an at- tacker may deceive this inference in very low probability, because an attacker can still send a packet with matched pair of source address and start field, and its mark may not be overwrit- ten.5. Practical ImplementationThe practical implementation of RPPM is based on Linux kernel 2.4.x and Netfil- ter/IPtables28). Linux has a 25 percent share in the operating system software market 29), thus our implementation can be deployed eas- ily. Netfilter/IPtables is a framework for packet mangling outside the normal Berkeley Socket interface.To control a packet mangling operation, aIn each hook point on the table, a packet mangling operation called target can be reg- istered. We provide three targets to ex- ecute marking, reflection, and reconstruc- tion algorithms: RPPM MARK, RPPM REFLCT, and RPPM RECONSTRUCT targets. Figure 8 locates the role of these targets and the working hook points. The detail of each targets are explained in the rest of this section.5.1 MarkingThe marking algorithm is implemented by the RPPM MARK target. Since this module works       
1856 IPSJ Journal Aug. 2003      root# iptables -t traceback -A POSTROUTING \ root# iptables -t traceback -A PREROUTING \ -j RPPM_MARK --prob <probability> -j RPPM_RECONSTRUCT --period <seconds>      Fig. 9 Using the RPPM MARK target. Fig. 11 Using the RPPM RECONSTRUCT target.                                        root# iptables -t traceback -A INPUT     \      -j RPPM_REFLECT --period <seconds> \      --smooth <smoothing constant>root# iptables -t traceback -A OUTPUT    \      -j RPPM_REFLECTroot# cat /proc/net/rppm_reconstructed_path[0]192.168.1.2 [1]192.168.1.1 [2]192.168.2.2[0]192.168.1.3 [1]192.168.1.1 [2]192.168.2.3Potential reflector: 192.168.1.2 (d=0)Potential reflector: 192.168.1.3 (d=0)                  Fig. 10 Using the RPPM REFLECT target.on POST ROUTING, the packets sent from local processes and those forwarded from other inter- faces can be marked equally. Figure 9 shows the command to use this module. In addition, it can automatically mark the particular inter- face address into a packet.5.2 ReflectionThe reflection algorithm is implemented by the RPPM REFLCT target. Figure 10 shows the command to use this module. To execute the storing procedure for statistics, it works at hook point LOCAL IN with the smoothing con- stant and the sampling period of statistics. The range of smooth is between 0 and 100, the rec- ommended argument is 30. The other argu- ment period is specified in seconds, the rec- ommended value can be led from Formula (2) described in Section 4.4.5.3 ReconstructionThe reconstruction algorithm is implemented by the RPPM RECONSTRUCT target. Figure 11 shows the command to use this module. The argument period is specified in seconds, being used to reset the collection of packets.This module shows the list of potential at- tack graph rooted by a victim with depth first search as well as collects packets. Cur- rent implementation provides this information through the Linux proc file system30), be- cause packets are collected in kernel space and do not need to copy all of them into user space, only the result of attack graph is enough. Figure 12 demonstrates a re- sult of a reconstructed path list by opening /proc/net/rppm reconstructed path.5.4 Applying RPPMWe arranged the applying RPPM at routers, reflectors, and victims as follows.At routersThe probabilistic packet marking should beFig. 12 List of reconstructed paths with two potential reflectors.conducted by RPPM MARK target shown in Fig. 9. The probability of packet marking is recommended to deploy identically among the routers.At reflectorsThe probabilistic mark reflection should be conducted by RPPM REFLECT target shown in Fig. 10. After reflection, the prob- abilistic packet marking should also be conducted by RPPM MARK target shown in Fig. 9, in order to tell their own addresses to a victim.At victimsThe reconstruction process should be con- ducted by RPPM RECONSTRUCT target shown in Fig. 11. To show the list of reconstructed path, open file as shown in Fig. 11.6. EvaluationWe conducted several evaluations to investi- gate the effectiveness of RPPM. The first eval- uation examines the effect of reflection algo- rithm. The second evaluation investigates the performance of our prototype implementation. Finally, the qualitative comparison of existing similar schemes and RPPM scheme is discussed.6.1 Effect of RPPM ReflectionThe effect of the reflection algorithm should not violate the semantics of PPM. In other words, the necessary number of packets to reconstruct paths at a victim should not be changed by the presence of reflection. To prove this ideal characteristic, we have evaluated the number of packets required to reconstruct paths of various distance d from 1 to 32 (it is more than almost all Internet paths 13),26) ), over 1,000 random test runs for each d before and af- ter reflection. In this evaluation, we connected an attacker A, router R, reflector Rf, and vic-           
Vol. 44No. 8Reflective Probabilistic Packet Marking Scheme for IP Traceback 1857       M (μsec) SD (μsec)         5.471.04 0.837 0.916 0.477 0.833         0.656 0.292 0.335 0.297 0.135 0.762                                                  2.22 4.21 4.13 3.29     0.609 0.854 0.8031.19                                                                       570 618 599   550 558 555                                                                                Fig. 13Number of packets for path reconstruction, with and without a reflection.Table 1 Performance of internal operations (M: mean, SD: standard deviation).Operations smplsRPPM MARKwrite a mark 20 overwrite a mark 30 add an end of edge 51 increment distance 482 do nothing 417 All       1000 RPPM REFLECT(input)increment count 456 add a new entry 16 update an entry 528 All       1000 RPPM REFLECT(ouput)decide not to mark 396 decide to mark 604 All       1000 RPPM RECONSTRUCTcollect a packet 1000 reconstruct a path 1000dure, we assumed flooding rate F as 1000 per second and necessary precision number P as 2, and sampling period T as 15 seconds (because d was 16). The result of mean and standard division are shown in Table 1.In marking procedure, writing a new mark consumes five times longer (5 microseconds in this case) than other marking operations. This overhead is caused by current Linux IP imple- mentation, which requires a copy of the packet to write the new IP option. We expect that IP options becoming more popular, the optimiza- tion of processing IP options will be enhanced.With regard to the reflecting procedure, espe- cially the operations that reflect a mark into an outgoing packet consumes more than hundred microseconds. Although the memory utiliza- tion simply depends on the number of routers, we allocated same memory size of hash space for each distance because of a simple imple- mentation. As a result, the further distance increases the number of routers in the attack path, thereby the hash space for closer distance are thinly used. In this situation, the reflecting procedure scans both used and unused mem- ory space in order to search the mark where total index and random index match. This in- efficiency linearly rebounded to the evaluation. For further optimization, closer distance hash space should be reduced by preparing different hash functions for each distance. The result of the optimized memory allocation will decrease the unused space exponentially, thus overhead will be reduced.   2.25 372   0.587 20.6   tim V with 100 BaseTX closed network. Each hosts was applied particular RPPM modules on Linux kernel 2.4.12 and Netfilter/IPtables 2.4 with a marking probability p = 0.05. Reflec- tion was conducted after packets traversed d- hop marking. We assumed flooding rate F as 1000 per second and necessary precision num- ber P as 2, and sampling period T as 40 seconds (because d was at most 32).In Fig. 13, we graph the mean and 95th per- centile of packet counts both before and after reflection. As shown in this result, each situ- ation of mean and 95th are approximately the same. Consequently, it indicates that by apply- ing RPPM modules the presence of reflection does not violate the semantics of PPM.In addition, most paths can be resolved with between one and two hundred, and even the longest paths can be resolved with less than six hundreds. This result shows that our scheme significantly reduces the number of packets for reconstruction compared with the preceding PPM schemes 6),11)6.2 PerformanceTo investigate the overhead of marking, re- flection, and reconstruction algorithms, we measured the performance of internal opera- tion in each function. For this experiment, we prepared two hosts (Celeron 400MHz and 128 Mbyte of RAM) connected by 100 BaseTX closed network, and assumed a marking prob- ability p is 0.05, distance d to the origin is 16. In this environment, we sent a burst of 1,000 packets and measured performance of each op- eration. In the evaluation of reflection proce-
1858Aug. 2003O(IP option field12-byte Yes Yessection: path validation and backward compat- ibility.7.1 Path ValidationAn attacker may gain access to routers along the path from attacker to victim. Furthermore, the attacker may control the routers to let them subvert the marking. The victim cannot dif- ferentiate between such malicious packets and genuine marked packets.In order to validate the reconstructed at- tack graph, one possible solution is to share the key among trusted routers and encrypt the mark. There are two approaches for sharing the key: an overlay network approach and path reservation approach. The overlay network ap- proach is attempted by Centertrack 14) , Cen- tertrack has a potential to create the network among trusted routers in order to share the key. The other, the path reservation approach has not yet explored, however existing archi- tecture such as RSVP 27) has a potential of key distribution platform. In addition, either the overlay network or path reservation approach can apply multiparty protocol such as simpli- fied VSS 31) , which enables to distribute the key into n routers, and decode even if m routers are malicious.7.2 Backward CompatibilityCurrently, our design and implementa- tion focused on IPv4 and ensured ICMP- compatibility. However, there are still differ- ent architectures such as IPv6, IP encapsulation (e.g., IPsec, tunneling, etc.). While we do not attempt to propose a complicated scheme also being dealt with such architectures, we believe that similar method can be applied.8. ConclusionIn this paper, we presented the design, im- plementation and evaluation of RPPM scheme, which is a traceback scheme against DDoS at- tacks including traffic laundered by reflectors. Our main contribution is that we have achieved traceback beyond the reflector attack which is6.3Table 2Reflector attacks ready Distributed attacks ready Managing cost Reconstruction complexity Encoding a mark into Additional data size ICMP-compatibility Practical implementationQualitative ComparisonRPPMYesYesTo compare characteristics with similar schemes and RPPM, we picked up two preced- ing schemes that adopt the end-host approach: conventional PPM scheme 6) and the ad- vanced probabilistic packet marking (APPM) scheme 11) . The result of qualitative compari- son is arranged in Table 2. The most apparent difference is the readiness for reflector attacks.While PPM scheme constrained its designwith single source attacks due to success the re-duction of each mark, the reconstruction com-plexity is O(  SdΨk) for DDoS attacks. On ddthe other hand, APPM dealt with multiplesource attacks by using a large set of hash func-tions and also retains the use of the IP Identi-fication field, that reduced the reconstruction complexity to O( d SdΨd). However, APPM assumed the upstream router map, which in- creased the managing cost for reflector attacks. Accordingly, preceding schemes were unwilling to discard the encoding into IP Identification field, PPM sacrificed the readiness of multiple source attacks and APPM increased the man- aging cost.In contrast, we have encoded a mark into the IP option fields in order to deal with multiple source attacks. At the same time, we do not require any additional information such as net- work map, the managing cost is minimal. Fur- thermore, a result of using the IP option field, we ensured ICMP-compatibility. Although the overhead of system may be increased by the use of the IP option field, the overhead can be con- trolled by possibility p and most routers become powerful enough to process IP options, we be- lieve that our scheme is feasible.Finally, whereas PPM and APPM only showed simulation results, we have imple- mented practically.7. Future WorkYet there are still a number of limitations, we state two main future research topics in thisIPSJ JournalComparing with other packet marking schemes.   PPM APPM  NoNoIP Identification field 0-byteNoNo    LowO(  SdΨk) dd           NoYes   High O( d SdΨd)IP Identification field 0-byteNoNo      Low d Sd) 
Vol. 44 No. 8 Reflective Probabilistic Packet Marking Scheme for IP Traceback 1859one of the hardest DDoS attacks in today’s In- ternet. We have extended PPM to render re- flectors ineffectual by reflecting marking statis- tics of incoming packets at reflectors. As well, we have encoded a mark into the IP option field to ensure ICMP-compatibility, whereas preceding schemes dismissed it. Thus, RPPM can traceback beyond reflectors, ensures ICMP- compatibility, and eliminates possibility of fail- ure in attack path reconstruction. Simulation results have shown RPPM retains the semantics of conventional PPM on a path between an at- tacker and a reflector. Also, its performance is almost feasible for practice, and we have shown the direction of optimization. We will develop our practical implementation further by open source in the near future. Although there are two main future research topics, path valida- tion and backward compatibility, we believe our scheme will be one of the best solutions towards an automated widely deployed traceback sys- tem.References1) Houle, K.J. and Weaver, G.M.: Trends in Denial of Service Attack Technology, Com- puter Emergency Response Team (2001). http://www.cert.org/archive/pdf/DoS trends.pdf2) Moore, D., Voelker, G.M. and Savage, S.: Inferring Internet Denial-of-Service Activity, USENIX Security Symposium (2001).3) Senie, D.: Network Ingress Filtering: Defeat- ing Denial of Service Attacks which employ IP Source Address Spoofing, RFC2827 (2000).4) Computer Emergency Response Team: CERT Advisory CA-2000-01 Denial-of-Service Devel- opments (2000). http://www.cert.org/ advisories/CA-2000-01.html5) Paxon, V.: An Analysis of Using Reflec- tors for Distributed Denial-of-Service At- tacks, ACM Computer Communication Re- view, Vol.31 (2001).6) Savage, S., Wetherall, D., Karlin, A. and Anderson, T.: Practical Network Support for IP Traceback, ACM SIGCOMM 2000, pp.295– 306 (2000).7) Asta Networks Inc.    http://www.astanetworks.com/8) Burch, H. and Cheswick, B.: Tracing anony- mous packets to their approximate source, USENIX Systems Administration Conference (LISA), pp.319–327 (2000).9) Bellovin, S.M.: ICMP Traceback Messages (2000). Internet Draft: draft-bellovin-itrace- 00.txt10) Barros, C.: A Proposal for ICMP Traceback Messages (2000). Internet Draft: draft-cesarb- itrace-01.txt11) Song, D. and Perrig, A.: Advanced and Au- thenticated Marking Schemes for IP Traceback, IEEE INFOCOM 2001 (2001).12) Cheswick, B. and Burch, H.: The Internet Mapping Project. http://cm.bell-labs.com/ who/ches/map/index.html13) Govindan, R. and Tangmunarunkit, H.: Heuristics for Internet Map Discovery, IEEE INFOCOM 2001, pp.1371–1380 (2001).14) Stone, R.: Centertrack: An IP Overlay Net- work for Tracking DoS Floods, USENIX Secu- rity Symposium (2000).15) Snoeren, A.C., Partridge, C., Sanchez, L.A. and Jones, C.E.: Hash-Based IP Traceback, ACM SIGCOMM 2001 (2001).16) Schnackenberg, D., Djahandari, K. and Strene, D.: Infrastructure for intusion detection and response, First DARPA Information Sur- vivability Conference and Exposition (2000).17) Snort. http://www.snort.org/18) Zhang, Y. and Paxon, V.: Detecting SteppingStone, USENIX Security Symposium (2000). 19) Computer Emergency Response Team: CERT Advisory CA-96.26 Denial-of-Service via pings(1996). http://www.cert.org/advisories/   CA-96.26.ping.html20) Paxon, V.: End-to-End Routing Behaivor in the Internet, IEEE/ACM Transactions on Net- working, Vol.5, No.5, pp.601–605 (1997).21) Stoica, I. and Zhang, H.: Providing guaran- teed services without per flow mangagement, ACM SIGCOMM 1999, pp.89–94 (1999).22) Jacobson,V.:CongestionAvoidanceandCon- trol, ACM Computer Communication Review, Vol.18, No.4, pp.314–329 (1988).23) Everette, G. and Jr, S.: Exponential smooth- ing: The state of the art, Journal of Forecast- ing, Vol.4, No.1, pp.1–38 (1985).24) Bowerman, B.L. and O’Connell, R.T.: Time Series and Forecasting, Duxbury Press, North Scituate, Massachusetts (1979).25) Postel, J.: Internet Protocol, RFC791 (1981). 26) Cooperative Association for Internet DataAnalysis: Skitter Analysis.   http://www.caida.org/tools/measurement/skitter/27) Braden, R. and Zhang, L.: Resource ReSerVa- tion Protocol, RFC2209 (1997).28) The Netfilter/IPtables project.   http://netfilter.samba.org/29) International Data Corp.   http://www.idc.com/30) Faulkner, R. and Gomes, R.: The Process File System and Process Model in UNIX Sys- 
1860 IPSJ JournalAug. 2003 31)tem V, USENIX Association Winter Confer- ence (1991).Gennaro, R., Rabin, M.O. and Rabin, T.: Sim- plified VSS and Fast-track Multiparty Compu- tations with Applications to Threshold Cryp- tography, ACM PODC ’98 (1998).(Received November 29, 2002) (Accepted June 3, 2003)Nobuhiko Nishio was born in 1962. He received his B.E. and M.S. degree from the Uni- versity of Tokyo in 1986 and 1988, and Ph.D. degree from Keio University in 2000. He is currently an associate profes-Noriyuki Harashima has received his B.S. and M.S. de- gree from Keio University in 2000 and 2002 respectively. Re- ceiving his M.S., he is currently working for ACCESS Co., LTD. in engaged in research and devel-opement of Java related system software. His research interest is secure ubiquitous computing especially for IDS and traceback technology for distributed DoS attack in the Internet.Hideyuki Tokuda was born in 1952. He received his B.S. and M.S. degrees from Keio Uni- versity, in 1975 and 1977 and Ph.D. degree in Computer Sci- ence from the University of Wa- terloo in 1983. He is currently aProfessor in the Faculty of Environmental Infor- mation, Keio University. His research interests include real-time systems, multimedia systems, mobile systems, communication protocols, mas- sively parallel/distributed systems and embed- ded systems. His current research interests are ubiquitous computing and networking systems. He is a member of the IEEE, the ACM, the IPSJ and JSSST. He is currently the chair of the SIGUBI in IPSJ.  sor at Ritsumeikan University BKC and a re- searcher at PRESTO of JST. Since 1993 till 2003 he had worked at Keio University SFC and got Yamashita memorial research award in 1994. His current research interests are ubiqui- tous computing and wireless ad-hoc sensor net- works. He is a member of the IPSJ, the IEEE- CS and the ACM. 